<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Refractoria disputatio: or, The thwarting conference, in a discourse between [brace] Thraso, one of the late Kings colonels. Neutralis, a sojourner in the city. Prelaticus, a chaplain to the late King. Patriotus, a well-willer to the Parliament. All of them differently affected, and disputing on the subjects inserted after the epistle, on the dissolution of the late Parliament, and other changes of state.</title>
            <author>T. L. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1502_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867582</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867582</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1502[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Refractoria disputatio: or, The thwarting conference, in a discourse between [brace] Thraso, one of the late Kings colonels. Neutralis, a sojourner in the city. Prelaticus, a chaplain to the late King. Patriotus, a well-willer to the Parliament. All of them differently affected, and disputing on the subjects inserted after the epistle, on the dissolution of the late Parliament, and other changes of state.</title>
                  <author>T. L. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 157, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White, and are to be sold by Thomas Brewster at the three Bibles in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Thraso, .. to the Parliament." bracketed on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: T.L.W.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 9 Nouemb: [the] 9:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Refractoria Diſputatio:</hi> OR, The Thwarting Conference, IN A DISCOVRSE, <hi>BETWEEN</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thraſo,</hi> One of the late Kings Colonels.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Neutralis,</hi> A ſojourner in the City.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prelaticus,</hi> A Chaplain to the late King.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Patriotus,</hi> A well-willer to the Parliament.</item>
               </list> All of them differently affected, and diſputing on the ſubjects inſerted after the Epiſtle, on the diſſolution of the late PARLIAMENT, and other changes of <hi>STATE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Porv.</hi> 12. 15. </bibl>
               <p>The way of a fool is right in his own eyes, but he that hearkneth unto counſel is wiſe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The wiſe man foreſeeth the evil to come, and preventeth it,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Brewſter</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard 1654.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the intelligent <hi>Reader,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Royaliſt, Malignant, or howſoever affected.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a facete obſervation of <note n="*" place="margin">Mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tague <hi>in his Eſſays.</hi>
               </note> a Perſon of honour, that a diligent Reader may apprehend more then the Author himſelf ever meant or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; If then it ſhall be either thy fortune or neglect in reading this <hi>Thwarting Conſerence,</hi> to underſtand leſs then is intended for the general inſtruction, that's the Readers fault none of the Authors; If ſo much as is preſented for the rectification of particular mens judgements (doubtful of their own principles) and unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in their minds; here is that which
<pb facs="tcp:119898:4"/> (if they be afore-hand not infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) will compoſe their diſtractions; out of the whole, the Reader may recollect his memory in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of State as haply are either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten or unknown unto him, and ſo he may take a review of things paſt as they were caried on in their vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and myſtical traverſes of Court, and thence to foreſee what may be the event of the late miraculous change of Government. If on thy firſt view of the Title, thou findeſt any itching deſire to know the ſcope and whereat the Diſcourſe ayms (as all novelties provoke appetite) take this in the way of an advertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that here are <hi>vetera, vera, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaque intermixta,</hi> old, true, and new paſſages, curſorily preſented in an interlocutory Conference; then look over to the next page, and haply the Contents may ſet a new edge on thy deſires; then read all or none; and not unlikely thou mayſt go very neer henceforth to know how to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:119898:4"/> thy ſelf to the beſt advantage under the preſent powers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with judge of the univerſal deſtiny of the Nation, ſhould it revert into Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; and on caſting up of thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, take theſe following Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions into thy more ſerious conſideration; firſt, with what labor, travel, care, and vexation of ſpirit, the two late Kings even from the very Ingreſs to their Crowns, to the period of their days, prepared the way to their own ruines, by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing their ambitious deſigns of heightning their Soveraignties above and beyond the bounds and limits thereof; whereas with much honour, love, loyalty, content, and profit to themſelves, peace, pleaſure, ſecurity, and tranquillity to their Subjects, they might have ſpent thoſe their vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious days in the full fruition of all worldly happineſs; But intoxicated with thoſe reſtleſs deſires of greatneſs and of ambition, to climb above the right end and orb of Government,
<pb facs="tcp:119898:5"/> and inflamed with thoſe over-high heats of ſtrengthning themſelves with that frail ſupport of the arm of fleſh, verified in that their long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and chargable negotiations, to contract Alliances, and intermar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages with <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of contrary and Idolatrous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions (aſpirations) which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet proſperous to Princes, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (as they pretended) the purity of Religion without intetmixtures; what Apologies and Defences have been made either by themſelves (living) or by others ſurviving and expoſed to the world, in vindication of their actions and too too manifeſt errors, are no other then the ſuperfluity and fineneſs of mens wits, byaſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out judgement to diſcern between truth and falſhood, the infallible te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of humane frailty and the Devils juglings, onely to deceive the common belief, whereas truth is ſtill the ſame, and will one day clearly appear and diſcover thoſe dark
<pb facs="tcp:119898:5"/> traces and ambages of the greateſt Maſters of Art and Policy, though for a time they may be inveloped and hidden from the ſight of the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and happily predominate on the credulity of too many that think themſelves wiſe above the ordinary ſort; yet at length they muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask't and layd open to the Worlds view; for <hi>magna eſt veritas, &amp;c.</hi> and it cannot be reſiſted. 'Tis moſt true, they were: Princes of great parts and endowments, though now in another World, whether we muſt all follow to render an accompt of our Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; howſoever without prejudice to their memories, both for our own and the inſtruction of poſterity, we may take into obſervation what they were living, and what inſtruments they made uſe of for carying on their ambitious Deſigns, to their own diſhonour, the blemiſh of their fames, the diſturbance of their domeſtick peace, the publick tranquillity, and of that ſecure ſettlement which the
<pb facs="tcp:119898:6"/> old King found here in a moſt perfect eſtabliſhment on the deceaſe of that unparalleld Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and as to the late moſt unfortunate King to the deſtruction of three flouriſhing Kingdoms, himſelf, his Poſterity, the Royalty, and the ruine of many of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commons of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Scene, we may take a ſhort view of that remarkable fate which befel the Authors, Promoters, Incendiaries, and principal Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, both Eccleſiaſtical and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, both before and throughout the whole managery of the late prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious War, and work of darkneſs to their own ruine, as a juſt reward to ſuch as in aſſiſtance and advance of a lawleſs and unlimited Soveraignty, moſt unnaturally and treacheouſly ſteered in the Regal courſe of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and well-nigh to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of more abſolute power over the three Nations, then ever was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted on the Theator of this
<pb facs="tcp:119898:6"/> Kingdom; whence we may learn and ſet up our reſts on theſe infallible <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſilium malum conſultoribus peſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> evil counſel is moſt inauſpicious to the Councellours themſelves; and on that other which by lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we have found moſt true,
<q>
                  <p>Quicquid delirant Reges, plectuntur Achivi:</p>
               </q> whatſoever Kings project, the poor innocent people muſt ſuffer for all and for their faults.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, to come a little neerer unto you, and more openly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain my ſelf; you have in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, not onely a part of the old caſe between King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament curſorily diſputed, but what the iſſue (in all probability) will be, in caſe the <hi>Scotch</hi> King cometh in by the ſword, with the fearful conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof, both in relation to your ſelves and the univerſal people; ye may by the way remember what
<pb facs="tcp:119898:7"/> work the late King made in all parts of the Land whereſoever his Armies and Garriſons were, how many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he made the conſtant ſeats of a furious and bloody War; how long he continued to embrew the land with innocent blood even to deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in how many places the poor Inhabitants had neither bread left them to eat, nor houſes wherein to put their heads; and that had his power been anſwerable to his will, how much worſe it would have been with the whole Nation, had the <hi>Danes, French, Lorra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nres, Scots,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> came to his Aſſiſtance; all which how earneſtly he ſolicited their coming over, his own Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to <hi>Cockrans,</hi> his Letters to the Queen, <hi>Montroſs</hi> and <hi>Ormond,</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declare; Yet there are of you that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re publickly ſay, that you are not aſhamed to own his cauſe, and diſown the Parliaments, which is no good ſign of your eternal being, when
<pb facs="tcp:119898:7"/> you are known to glory in evil, and ſtand fixed in the defence of him, and a cauſe that was moſt unjuſt in the beginning, bloody (beyond exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) throughout the whole managery, tragical in the end to himſelf, loſs of honor, eſtate, and fortunes of moſt that ſided with him; and ſhould the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender come in, how much worſe and more oppreſſive and more bloody it muſt be, I leave to your own conſideration.</p>
            <p>For a cloſe, I wiſh you all better to bethink your ſelves, and take this into your more ſerious thoughts of the wiſeſt of men; <hi>He that juſtifieth the wicked, and condemneth the juſt, even they both are abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 17. 15. Then as you pleaſe, read on, and haply you may finde ſomewhat that will terrifie your conſciences, or rectifie your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in your erroneous princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and turn the torrent of your depraved affections to a hearty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance
<pb facs="tcp:119898:8"/> with the preſent Powers, as they are ſet over us by the hand of the Almighty, which doubtleſs, is the beſt and ſafeſt courſe you can take for your future happineſs;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which that you may enjoy, are the hearty wiſhes of an unknown yet your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained friend</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119898:8"/>
            <head>The principal Contents of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p n="1">1. OF the neceſſity of continuing the Contributions on the people, with the Reaſons thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the hopes wherewith Royaliſts flatter themſelves in mending their fortunes, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the States Power, and ſtrength for upholding the preſent Government.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of the difficulties which attend the <hi>Scotch</hi> Kings coming in, being to invade by Sea.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of the parallel between the <hi>Hollanders</hi> caſe and this of the States here in their firſt eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Of the miſerable condition that of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity muſt befal this Nation, eſpecially the City of <hi>London,</hi> in caſe the <hi>Scotch</hi> King comes in by the ſword, with the conſequences of changing the Laws, and conſtitutions of the old Soveraignty.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Of King <hi>James</hi> his plot, for abating the power of Parliaments, and improvement of the Soveraignty, by diſowning them, furthered by the Biſhops, and purſued by the late King.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb facs="tcp:119898:9"/>8. Of the neceſsitated Reaſons that induced the Parliament to cut off the late King, and to exclude his Poſterity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether the preſent eſtabliſhment in the nature of a Republick, accompanied with the Taxes impoſed on on the people, will not be more ſafe and leſs chargeable to them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender to the Regal Government.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Of the grand objection of Royaliſts, that the late Parliament was not a legal Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of the people, after it was lamed, leſſned by want of the King, the Lords, Prelates, and major part of the Commons excluded; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That the Parliaments after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>Norman,</hi> the <hi>Witengagoment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and thoſe <hi>magna Conſilia</hi> of the old <hi>Britains,</hi> were not always of one form, but one and the ſame in ſubſtance.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Of the various alterations and changes of Governments throughout all Ages of the World, and that all Powers had their original by the ſword, which once obtained, Whether by right or wrong, ought to be obeyed ſubmitted unto, as the Ordinance of God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119898:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Refractoria Diſputatio:</hi> OR, The Thawrting Conference.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, you are all well met; I perceive you are as good as your words; but now Signiour <hi>Patriotus,</hi> tell me what is become of your late piece of a Parliament; have they not enacted hand ſomely to Act them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of their uſurped powers, by their injuſtice and ſelf ends, without any reſpect either to the publick good, or any poor mans private intereſt? hath not God in his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice dealt with them, as they did with the late innocent King, and all of us of his ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ants? Tell me I beſeech you what will be the iſſue of this inter-meddly of Government, and whether in the end, confuſion will not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow theſe ſtrange mutations, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt taken of them for their extortions, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119898:10"/> corrupt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meanors towards the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patriotus.</speaker>
               <p>I finde you are ſtill in your old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one; but as in our laſt conference and elſewhere, I have often told you, ſo now, I ſhal not take upon me to juſtifie every of their actions; for they are men made up and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of fleſh and blood, ſubject to ſin and error; and that the ſame God who gave them the power they have had, would as ſoon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt them of it, as (beyond all expectation) he bequeathed it unto them, in caſe they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried not themſelves with an upright heart; As to thoſe your Prophetical iſſues to follow in confuſion, and of after-reckonings, may it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them that deſerve it; for my hope it, and I doubt not, but that Almighty God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his providence, on this great change of affairs, hath another manner of work in hand then lies within your kenning to diſcern, and will raiſe us up ſuch unbyaſſed Governors as ſhall ſet ſtraight all obliquities, both in the Church and State, to his own glory and the comfort of all good men; therefore let me adviſe y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, not to be too raſh in your cenſure, on that whereof you are not able to judge, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cant on his judgements, which are in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crutable and paſt your finding out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us.</speaker>
               <p>But <hi>Patriotus,</hi> I remember at our laſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erence, you alſo were pleaſed to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119898:10"/> vent your ſelf in the way of predictions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that we muſt expect worſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then heretofore we have endured, which as you then ſuppoſed, would of neceſſity befal the univerſal Nation, not onely in the continuation of the Contributions and Taxes impoſed on the people, but in other grievous afflictions, which I proſeſs have ever ſince very much troubled my cogitations; for God knows we have all ſuffered too much already, and more then the ability of poor people can longer endure; though I confeſs, for any thing I can as yet diſcern out of the motions of the State, the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions muſt of neceſſity be continued, if not encreaſ'd, for maintenance of their Armies both by Land and Sea, and not unlikely will be long lived, and continued for a Prenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, haply of ſeven years endurance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, <hi>Neutralis,</hi> and longer then you imagine; for conſidering the work the States at preſent have in hand, within our in-works, to ſuppreſs the malignant Party; and in our out-works, for defending the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Seas, againſt the invading and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful <hi>Hollander;</hi> we <note place="margin">The neceſsity of the continuation of the Contributions of the people.</note> cannot in any reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any ceſſation or remiſſion of our Taxes, but that conſtanrly they will be continued,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119898:11"/> if not encreaſed; and of this we have a preſident in the change of the Government in the <hi>Nether-Lands;</hi> where, on their revolt from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the States were enforc'd to raiſe their Exciſe on all things which the Natives did eat or drink, and to impoſe Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms on all ſorts of Merchandize, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported or exported; without which, they could never have been enabled to pay their Armies, and to wage war with ſo potent a Prince as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and that for 80 years endurance at leaſt; which ſhewes out unto us what we are to expect, even a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of our Taxes, and well it would be if we eſcape ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prela.</speaker>
               <p>Its a fine liberty and freedom then, that the late Parliament and your reformers have procured to the Nation; and indeed <hi>Patriotus,</hi> I am of your opinion, that the States here (as you ſtile them) muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity continue, if not encreaſe the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, when as all the Kings Lands and goods, the Biſhops and Delinquents Eſtates are ſold and ſpent, and when the King comes in to multiply their charge, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them for payment of their Armies, to take any thing (as often they have done) whereſoever the Souldier can finde it; there being but one only way left us to preſerve the Nation from utter ruine and a final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119898:11"/>Neut.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech you Doctor, what one way is that? I ſhall be very thankful unto you to ſhew me that learning, that ſo we may ſee an end of our miſeries, and that ſuch as my ſelf (who never bore Arms on either ſide, neither had a hand in ſhedding of one drop of blood) might come at length to know the uttermoſt of our pain, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy our wonted tranquillity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>In brief <hi>Neutralis,</hi> 'tis the admiſſion of the King to his Royal Rights; for without a King, and the reſtitution of the Crown-Lands, and the Churches Patrimony, never expect an end of our calamities, but an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting war, with the continuation of the Taxes, and oppreſſions of the poor people, ſo long as thoſe innocent Princes of the Royal Line are unjuſtly kept out of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; the example whereof we may ſee in <hi>Holland,</hi> very judiciouſly even now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced by <hi>Patriotus,</hi> to whoſe judgement I appeal, as the readieſt and ſureſt remedy to cure the convulſions of the Land, and to ſettle peace throughout the three Nations, which otherwiſe is impoſſible to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, give me leave to diſſent from your Opinion, and in the firſt place, to remember you of that wherewith even now you and the Colonel taxed the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119898:12"/> with, the oppreſſions of the people, wherein you over-ſhoot the mark without looking to the original cauſes and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which have enforc't the States to impoſe thoſe payments on the Natives, which are neceſſitated for keeping the poor people from farther bloodſhed and oppreſſion: 'Tis in part true, that in caſe the King of <hi>Scots</hi> could be as readily admitted as you ſpeak it, and in a peaceable and ſafe way for the Nation, both in reſpect of the preſent and ſuture ſecurity, it might haply conduce ſomewhat toward a preſent ſettelment of affairs for a time, which would not be either long or laſting, but never disburthen us of our payments; for as the caſe now ſtands, on admiſſion of any one of the late Kings Linage, he would doubtleſs on all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities have an <hi>animum revertendi,</hi> a minde to the old way, <hi>viz.</hi> to rule at will and pleaſure, (an ambition inſeparably united to the Sep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of all Kings, eſpecially to theſe which claim ſucceſſively and <hi>de jure Coronae;)</hi> ſo that in a ſhort time, we ſhould be <hi>in ſtatu quo priùs</hi> enforc't to fight over again &amp; again the old quarrel fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſervation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Liberty; Therefore I beſeech you Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, conſider well of the preſent condition wherein we are, together with the ſetled re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the State here in being, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119898:12"/> have not onely taken away the late Kings life, as the onely remedy left them to ſettle a firm peace; but farther have reſolved to exclude his Poſterity, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not holding the Fathers blood either a ſufficient expiation for the infinity of blood ſpilt throughout the three Nations, or the Royalties and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of the Crown, neither the Lands of the Biſhops (which without all queſtion were the grand ſticklers and promoters of all our late concuſſions) a competent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the injuries and loſſes ſuffered by the three Nations, but in deteſtation of Kingly Government (whence through all Ages hath proceeded ſuch numberleſs op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and imbroylments) never to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any more Kings; beſides, you may take it in the way, what an eſſay the States have already made for the ſettlement o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an <hi>Ariſtocratical</hi> Government, in im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>acion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er their cuting of <hi>Tarquin us</hi> and his Poſterity for Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anny; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of later days<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the States of <hi>Holland</hi> have done, and proſperouſly accomphſhed; I app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al to your own judgement, (whether the King of <hi>Scots</hi> coming in by ſorce of Arms or not at all) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll
<note place="margin">The deſtructive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch</hi> Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in by the ſword.</note> not plunge the Nation into an irreparable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? yea, into ten degrees worſe then at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119898:13"/> preſent we are in? and that of neceſsity i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be ſo, and can be no other; pleaſe you to have patience, I ſhail render you many infallible reaſons, and ſuch as I believe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gainſaid; beſides, 'tis well known, that the preſent Pretender is affected, haply infected with his Fathers principles of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Soveraignty, which will never ſute with the genius of the States here in being, which have the ſtaffe in their hands, with the Powers and ſtrengths of all the Land at their only command, and for ought I can perceive, are both able &amp; intentive to uphold the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, and ſo to eſtabliſh it, that in mans reaſon its impoſsible to diveſt them otherwiſe then by a ſtronger power, which I believe lies not within the <hi>Scotch</hi> Kings reach to compaſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>Doubt not you of that; for the King is not ſo deſtitute of friends and means to accompliſh his deſigns as you imagine; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I of your opinion that the Kings coming in will make our condition worſe then now it is; for worſer it cannot be; but on the contrary, he will out of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate goodneſs and compaſſion towards the poor oppreſſed people, relieve them in what poſſibly he may, and that by an act of Oblivion, all old grutches with the late diſſentions ſhall be coffin'd up and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119898:13"/> in his gracious and general pardon to all parties; And I am cleerly of opinion that there can be no ſafer and readier way to compoſe all feuds and differences to eaſe the people of their Contributions, and reeſtabliſh an everlaſting peace throughout the three Nations, then the acceptance of his Majeſty to be our King, as of right he ought to be, and as I doubt not ere long he ſhall be in ſpight of all his enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eech you, let us reaſon this caſe amongſt our ſelves in moderation, and with patience, and let the firſt Quere be whether the States Government, as 'tis now ſetled, or ſhortly may be, with our preſent Contributions for payment of their Armies, wil not be more ſafe and eaſie for the people, then the Scotch Pretenders coming in by force of Arms to aſſume the Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Since, by a peaceable and conditional way, I ſuppoſe, he will never be admitted; So that Doctor, without all queſtion he hath no choice left him, but that of the ſword, and then judge you of the iſſue, and into what a lamentable condition the poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives will neceſſarily be reduced, when the right of the crown comes again to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, the king (as you would have him) being perſonally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; And after this Quere, Let us compute
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119898:14"/> the hopes, helps, ſtrengths, and aſſiſtances, whereon both parties may dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of each others cauſe; For one battel either by Sea or Land, happily will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the controverſie, as twas conceived by ſome, that one battel (as that at <hi>Edghill)</hi> in the begining of the late wars would decide the buſineſs, which proved to be like the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulation of the Monſter <hi>Hidra's</hi> head, which begot others <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and when the late King was in perſon in the head of his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my. <note place="margin">Of the hopes, aſſiſtances and Forces which the <hi>Scotch</hi> King may have to recover the Kingly Government, compared with the ſtrengths the States have to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, argued on all hands.</note> I ſay then, Let us make an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtimate of the forces and aſſiſtances of each party; which on a due examination, and on conſideration of that which muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow, when at once (as we may conjecture) two, four, or happily ſix ſeveral Armies may be in the field, will be ſo far from eaſing, or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sburchening of the people, that what by free Quartering, and inforcing of contributions by one or the other party, that the Natives will curſe the time that ever your King came amongſt them. Now Gentlemen, do one of you tell me, what Forces and Aſſiſtances (as you conceive) the King may have or preſume upon; for I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119898:14"/> believe he will come ſhort of his expectation in receiving any conſiderable Aſſiſtance, either from the <hi>Scotch,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and then I will tell you, that which all men and your ſelves do know to be moſt true, what the States here have, and may have, as well in their preſent power by Sea and Land, as by their Politique managery, in faſtning friends unto them, whereby to make good the preſent eſtabliſhment: Colonel, You being a Souldier, and (not unlikely) having better Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, from abroad, then any of us, what preparations the <hi>Scots</hi> King hath in forraign parts, what friends at home and elſewhere, begin you if you pleaſe, and I will rejoyn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart; In the firſt place I'le aſſure you, that ſince the death of the late King my Royal Maſter, his Majeſty that now is, whom the States here would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, hath ten friends for one, more then he had before, thoughout the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; ſo much your States have gotten by the bargains in Martyring their King: neither ought you to believe, but that the King hath both in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> a very conſiderable party that will joyn with him as ſoon as he arrives, and not a few even in the City of <hi>London,</hi> which expect a good time, though they lie ſtill and quiet; however the King hath their hearts, and will have their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119898:15"/> hands on all fitting occaſions; Beſides, He hath at his devotion all the Catholikes, and moſt of the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> with all the Lords, ſo lately and Injuriouſly thruſt out of their houſe, together with the better part of the Members of the Commons houſe, pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed out by the ears, by the Independent Soulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all which refuſed to take the Engagement, and when time ſerves will appear in Arms for him, beſides all the
<note place="margin">The <hi>Scotch</hi> Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hopes in aſſiſtance for recovery of the Crown, ſummed up.</note> old Royal party Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Realm for their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to their old Maſter: Thus much for the ayds and aſſiſtances his Majeſty may relie on from his own Subjects; And as to his forraign aſſiſtance, you may reſt aſſured that all the Princes through Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (when the time ſerves) will engage for him, ſince it ſtands them upon ſo to do; Neither may you doubt but that all the Princes, his neer Kinſmen, and Allyes will furniſh him plentifully with all ſorts of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and the Hollanders with ſhipping, ſo ſoon as they have maſtered the Seas, and made all things ready for an Invaſion; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it as an evident truth, that in the preſent quarrel by Sea between them and this State, the Kings Intereſt is involved, and will be purſued, notwithſtanding their late bruſh which they reckon not of, neither of a few
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119898:15"/> inconſiderable Ships, they having enough of others to recrute in a trice; ſo that you may evidently ſee, that as ſoon as time ſerves, the King cannot want men: and for mony, good Swords and Piſtols will fetch it in with a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; Whence you may diſcern what an unwildy task the late piece of a Parliament, and theſe new ſprang-up States have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and what will neceſſarily befall them, through their own diviſions &amp; when the King appears in power, (as of that you may be ſure, he will ſooner then you think on) then you ſhall ſee a world of the Parliaments friends to fall from them, &amp; for their own ſakes will fight for him; and probable it is, that a good number of the States Souldiers, now in their pay, on his Majeſties landing (with another manner of equipage then all of you are aware of) will run from them to him, with all their hearts as their indubitable Lord &amp; Soveraign.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Partri.</speaker>
               <p>Colonel, you have indeed ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly ſumm'd up what Forces (as you ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) the King may have and expect both at home and from abroad: wherein you are very much miſtaken, and do reckon without your hoſt; you ſpeak rather what you would have, then in reaſon what the King can have: ſtill diſcovering your malignant heart, and flattering your ſelf (as moſt of your party uſe to do) with vain and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119898:16"/> hopes, not conſidering how the late King, notwithſtanding all his wyles and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, fail'd in all his deſigns and practiſes, and at laſt, brought him ſelf and his friends to utter ruine, to the great detriment and deſolation of three Kingdoms, ſtill ſoothing up himſelf with the goodneſs of his cauſe (which was as bad as bad might be) to the laſt gaſpe; neither take you the leaſt notice of Gods providence in the diſpoſure of this wonderful work and change of Affairs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the continued ſeries of the many mita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Victories which it hath pleaſed God to give to the States Armies, wherein the very hand of the Almighty is moſt perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous to all good men; but to you and your complices hidden and unſeen, even to obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and hardning of your hearts. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Poet methinks ſhould teach you, <hi>Quos u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt perder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jupiter dementat,</hi> whom God intends to deſtroy, he blinds and hardens them as he did <hi>Pharoah.</hi> But Colonel; I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, on your better conſideration, tell me what aſſiſtance can the Princes the Kings kindred afford him, were they able and willing to ayd him? and in what Region are they, and <note place="margin">The States power and ſtrengths at preſent.</note> in what Climate we? are we not both ſevered by the vaſt Ocean? I ſhall tell you a ſtory, and of one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119898:16"/> of the greateſt Princes Chriſtian of his time, even the Emperour <hi>Charls</hi> the Fifth, who on a defiance ſent him by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, made this Anſwer to the Herald, <hi>Tell my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle from me, he talks big, and like the Fox in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> burrow when he knows himſelf in ſafety, ſo your Maſter environed with the Sea, but were he on the Continent, happily then he might be talkt withal on better terms then he ſends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e:</hi> You may gue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s at the application. What hurt I pray can the Kings of <hi>France, Spain, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> with other the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> do to this State (in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane judgement) as
'tis an Iſland environed with the vaſt Ocean, provided with all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Abiliments of War both by Sea &amp; Land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could their own domeſtick wars, jealouſies, and differences give them leave to attempt againſt this State: Which without doubt is backed by the power of Heaven, had you the grace to ſee it, &amp; therewith to call to mind in what ſtrength the late King was but 1645, and of how many ſtrong Garriſons poſſeft, and what Armies, (almoſt) in every County of the Land; how many of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity &amp; prime Gentry in every Province at his devotion, how powerful in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> and yet within 15 Moneths beaten in all places, his many Garriſons and him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elf taken. Look upon the attempts of his Son,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119898:17"/> whom all of you ſo much adore and deſire, that he would purſue his obſtinate Fathers quarrel to the further deſtruction of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; look upon the <hi>Scots</hi> beaten under <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleton</hi> with the whole Nation, by the now Lord General <hi>Cromwel;</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> likewiſe reduced by him, and the King himſef with his powerful Army beaten to flitters at <hi>Worceſter;</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at Sea; and yet all of you of the Royal Party ſtill flatter your ſelves with vain hopes, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embroyling the Nation in a new War, which can be to no other effect but to the ruine of your ſelves, in kicking againſt the pricks, and the immediate hand of the Almighty. Now Colonel, I ſhall tell you particularly what the States Forces are at preſent, and what a poſture of defence and offence they are in, and will be on any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion from abroad, or riſing at home; Firſt, they are poſſeſt of all the Forts, Ports, Caſtles, and Ammunion of the Land, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a very great Naval Force, and as occaſion requires, more they may and will have; the whole revenue of the Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at their command; Moreover, they have a very great veteran and Victorious Army, ready diſciplin'd on all occaſions, under their pay, and maintain'd at the Natives charge, all the Commanders and Souldiers inured to the Wars, and as I may ſay, of one Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119898:17"/> and fraternity, ſuch as knows each others minds, and what they are to do on all Invaſions and home-bred diſturbances; and this is obvious to all men, and known to your ſelves, when as all thoſe numbers you ſpeak of to be here for the King hand and heart, yet is it evident they will never be able to imbody to any purpoſe, but will be cut all in pieces whenſoever they attempt it, and that by the States horſe diſperſed throughout the Land: Again, You muſt of neceſsity admit that the <hi>Scotch</hi> King can never make his preparations ſo ſilent, but that ſuch is the vigilance of the States (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever his rendezvouz ſhall be) but that they will have particular intelligence thereof, and will be ready with a powerful Fleet to impead the tranſport of any conſiderable Army ſo ſoon as it puts out to Sea, and to fight or ſink them before ever they ſhall ſet one foot on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground; and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Naval Forces be never ſo great, without all queſtion, the States Flect here will be every way equivalent; ſo that on a right judgment to be made, the <hi>Scotch</hi> King hath a far more difficult task in hand (being to invade by
<note place="margin">Of the difficulty that the <hi>Scotch</hi> King bath to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade by Sea.</note> Sea) then any of us can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine: Beſides, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what numbers of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119898:18"/> Gentry and Yeomandry of the Land are tied and fixed to the States, and moſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Troopers which have bought much of the Kings and Biſhops Lands, are all bound to fight as well for the Venders in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt as their own; ſo that you may be ſure they will rather ſtand to the work for their own ſakes, then run to the King to their own undoing; now beſides all this already recited, I pray take into conſideration, the terror which the late ſequeſtrations have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt on all Delinquents and adherents to the late King, with the preſent poverty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of all that party, which both diſables and diſheartens them to arm in the behalf of a King that eats no other bread then that of Alms-deed: Tis true, there is a numerous party in the Land both of cloſe and open Malignants, ſome whereof (anſwerable to their old humour) will talk big and at large in the Kings behalf; but to fight afreſh for him, they will be very cautious, eſpecially thoſe which have any thing left them to loſe, and when they very well know how many Watches and Sentinels attend their motious th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oughout all corners of the Land.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prelat.</speaker>
               <p>Its moſt true, that the King hath a very difficult task in hand for the recovery of his rights, (oeing to inwade by Sea) if we reaſon <hi>ad captum humanum,</hi> according to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119898:18"/> mans underſtanding; but 'tis far otherwiſe, when we come to conſider what God will do, who never forſakes the righteous cauſe, but in his own good time never fails to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and help the afflicted, when they leaſt think on't and when; he that knows his own time will confound the wicked, and ſuch as moſt impiouſly have intruded on the Regal Rights, with the adminiſtration of juſtice to the people, which with what equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they meaſure out unto them, your own knowledge and the clamours of many an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man can beſt reſtifie. Now as to your late inſtance in the <hi>Hollanders</hi> revolt, and with what ſucceſs they encountred ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an Adverſary as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> worſted him and eſtabliſhed their <hi>Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Government, and in humane reaſon have ſo fortified it that they ſeem impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; between this caſe and the late Kings there is a great difference; for as your ſelf hath obſerved, the grounds and reaſons of their revolt firſt ſprang from the impetuous demeanor and Tyranny of <hi>Don Alvas de Toledo,</hi> who as <hi>Lipſius</hi> reports, in that ſhort time of his Vice-Roy-ſhip, put to death and maſſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſo few as 100000 of the Natives, amongſt which the Counts <hi>Egmont</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi> with others of the Nobility, were the chief which withſtood his Tyranny, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119898:19"/> ſtood up in defence of their immunities, which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> by power would have taken from them; which was a juſt cauſe given to the people to revolt, both for ſafegard of their lives and priviledges, which the four great Dukes of <hi>Burgandy</hi> ſuffered them to enjoy; ſo that on a right underſtanding of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> caſe, which was juſt and but reaſon, that when they could not obtain right from the King upon their many Petitions and complaints of the Tyranny of his Miniſters, they could do no leſs then endeavor the preſervation of their lives and fortunes; And therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> they ſeized on divers of the ſtrongeſt Towns, and the people unanimouſly fell in with the Prince, and ever ſince manfully and fortunately have defended themſelves. But in the late defection of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with the Parliaments raiſing of Armies againſt their Soveraign Lord, there is no manner of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude with that of <hi>Holland,</hi> or any ſuch cauſe given or ground of the peoples defection; ſince I preſume you will confeſs that not ſo much as one guiltleſs man (during all the late Kings raign) hath been put to death, unleſs you object and inſtance in thoſe which by the fatality of the late War befel both parties, which you know to be no other then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119898:19"/> 
                  <hi>fortuna de la gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra,</hi> not the Kings Tyranny or the leaſt deſire of his that a drop of innocent blood ſhould have been ſpilt; and that which was, was in his own neceſsitated defence. But I pray take the caſe as now it ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the preſent King and your States, then you may ſoon ſee the difference; for in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Collonels aſſertion, I dare affirm the King hath ten friends for one to thoſe on whom the States may rely as firm and fixed to them ſince his late Majeſty was put to death; and that major number, (you may be ſure on'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) are all his in body and ſoul, and do utterly deteſt that his Royal Father and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf ſhould be ſo unjuſtly cut off and excluded of his birth-right; and by whom think you, but by an inconſiderable part of the repreſentative, the Souldiery, and a handful of the people theirs adherents? and therefore I ſay, that the King on a right eſtimate of his party, upon the leaſt turn of the wheel will have a ſurerer and a ſtronger ſide then poſſibly the States here can have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, in this your laſt reply, I obſerve ſome notable particulars; firſt you approve of the juſtneſs of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; yet you ſay, that it parrallels not with this of the States here and change of the Government; the reaſons you have given
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119898:20"/> for juſtifying the <hi>Hollander,</hi> I confeſs are moſt true, ſelf preſervation being juſt and allowable by Gods Law and mans; But that now you ſhould defend their cauſe, which none of your ſaid party ever did till of late, is ſomewhat ſtrange, unleſs it be for that (as you believe) they are ſecretly engaged in the <hi>Scotch</hi> Kings Cauſe; and yet you condemn the late Parliament for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending themſelves and their liberties againſt the late Kings Tyranny, which you ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endevor to excuſe, and would quit him from all blood-guiltineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. To which I anſwer, That had you thought upon your own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of 100000, of the Natives maſſacred by the Tyranny of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> it would have put you in minde of a million of people throughout the three kingdoms ſlain and murthered, by the meer Tyranny, Plots and practiſes of the late King, of which you take no notice, but after the wonted manner of all Royaliſts, you juſtiſty his innocency; ſo that to the worlds-end you give occaſion to the Parliaments party to rip up the faults of the dead, and cauſe them to diſplay all his Falſhoods, frauds, breaches of Oaths and Proteſtations: But as to your aſſertion, That the major number of the people here, are for the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender in body and ſoul, is in part granted you, yet therein you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119898:20"/> delude your ſelf; for the odds in that major number will little advantage him or his party, ſince the major power lies evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the leſſer number which are for the States; what then? will it avail a prince (unexperienced) to lead a great yet an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſciplin'd Army, againſt a leſſer number but well diſciplin'd, valiant and armed Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; though you cannot be ignorant that the States Armies are very ſtrong and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous in all the three Nations. As to your denyall of the ſimilitude and parallel, I ſay on the ſame reaſons that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> took up <note place="margin">The <hi>Hollanders</hi> caſe and of the States here al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke parallel.</note> arms in defence of their liberties, the people here did the ſame for defence of themſelves and their Repreſentative; ſo that the parallel on the actions of both States holds and is alike, ſave only in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nanimity and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal promptitude of the <hi>Nether Lands</hi> in their joyning and uniting of all their Forces, with the Princes <note n="*" place="margin">Orange.</note> retinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; tis moſt true, the parallel in this holds not ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for I muſt confeſs the State of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and manner of the revolt of a part of the people from the late King is different, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains doubtful what may fall out in the iſſue, in reſpect that the other major part of the people are conceived ſtill to wiſh well to his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119898:21"/> Son the preſent Pretender, and that all the three Nations ſtand in a kinde of diſtracted condition, in regard that they are divided into parties, ſides, factions, fractions, fects, ſchiſms and opinions, which I acknowledge may ſooner mar the work of the States now in being then they are aware of. But in a word more to the point, that the major num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the people are for the <hi>Scocth</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender, I ſay again, that that number conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as they are a naked, awed, and dejected bulk of diſcontented animals, ſignifies little or nothing, compared with that power of which the States here are poſſeſt; neither in humane reaſon can we ſee how or by whom they can be diſpoſſeſt. But let us on all hands ſuppoſe that the preſent Pretender ſhall land again in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> (as of late he did, where you know he was beaten, there, and at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and forc'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for his life;) again, ſuppoſe he comes in with a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>merous Army of <hi>French, Dutch, Lorrainers, Germans, Sweeds, Dants,</hi> together with all the preſcribed Cavaleers, and all theſe united with a good party of <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> admit them to be in all 60000 fighting men (which will be too great an Army to be tranſported without a very powerful Navie) ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers you'l grant cannot ſtay long there, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they mean to eat one another; well
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119898:21"/> then, you will ſay, they may inſtantly march into <hi>England,</hi> (as of late they did) and not unlikely in two or three ſeveral bodies, and in divers ways, the more to diſtract our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; where you ought to remember that this State hath both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and the adjacent parts, a very conſiderable force to encounter theſe Invaders; but admit again, that the King advances ſo far as <hi>York,</hi> though you cannot imagine but that he will be fought with twice or thrice over before he comes thither with freſh men, and not unlikely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten, as at all places he hath been; but let us again admit that he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmounts all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both by Sea and Land, and becomes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, and triumphantly marches towards <hi>London,</hi> and that the States Force cannot withſtand him, and that on the noiſe of ſuch ſad news, the prevailing party (as you are pleaſed to ſtile them) being confound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with terrour, betake themſelves to their heels as their <hi>ultimum refugium,</hi> and the beſt way to ſhiſt for themſelves, and that after this, all is left to the Kings abſolute diſpoſement, (as all this not impoſſible, but exceeding impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,) what then, on ſuch ſudden change of fortune think you, may be the iſſnes thereof, and what advantage either to your party or the generality of the people, and all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries through which his Armies ſhall march
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119898:22"/> and Quarter, accompaned with ſo many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly affected?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs the people muſt ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſarily ſuffer, and haply in a greater meaſure then hitherto they have done; yet am I confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, his Majeſty will be very ſenſible of their ſufferings, and in prevention of their farther oppreſſion, and for ſettling of all things, will immediately call a new Parliament, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to the antient Form and Inſtitution of the three Eſtates, King, Lords Spiritual and Temporal, with the Commons, and then commit all things to a ſober, legal, and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentary diſcuſſion; and in what manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution may be made of his own Lands and goods, the Churches Patrimony, with the many other looſers of his own party; and after all this, in deteſtation of the foulneſs of the late War and bloodſhed, to bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y all diſcontents and heart-burnings (as Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> very j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diciouſly propoſes) in an Act of Oblivion, with free pardon to all, except ſome ſpecial perſons that had a principal hand in his Fathers death, and for all other of his Subjects, to ſpare and cheriſh them in what poſsible his affaits will permit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, excuſe me, ſince I utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from your opinion; for it ſtands not with reaſon, or with the Kings then preſent affaires to take a piece of that courſe, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119898:22"/> you ſuppoſe; and ſhould he be willing, there would be ſo many of the old Cavalry attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his perſon, as well Natives as Forraigners, which would thruſt in to be ſerved and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that he ſhould not be ſuffered to put in practiſe a title of that which is by you ſo vainly ſurmiſed; but you may build upon't, he would take a clean contrary courſe, and ſuch a one as the neceſſity of his then urgent occaſions would inforce, and not tie up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his own diſadvantage by an Act of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, which neceſſarily muſt diſable him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to help himſelf or friends, when the power is in his hands to do what he pleaſeth, and carve as he liſteth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>Since you are ſo diffident of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties good nature and intentions towards his Subjects, tell us I beſeech you, what you conceive he will do for the ſpeedy ſettling of peace and amity through the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>May I obtain your lice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and a favourable conſtruction of that which I ſhall deliver, I will tender my opinion, and leave you all to make your own judgments thereon: In the firſt place, I believe that whereas then he comes in by the ſword, in order to his neceſſities he would rule by the ſword and by an Army, with Garriſons throughout the Land, (as now the States up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119898:23"/> the point do and muſt do, if they mean to go through ſtitch with their work) and thenceforth begin a new Government (as in like manner the States here intend to do) the Laws of the Land (which under the preſent power the people yet enjoy, as they were wont to do in quiet and peaceable times) would neceſſarily be ſubverted and turn'd topſie-turvie, and ſuch introduced in their room as ſhould beſt ſute with the will and pleaſure of a Prince that comes in by Conqueſt, and by the ſame power will have them to be no other then agrees with his Affairs and reſolutions, or as they are in <hi>France,</hi> if not worſe and more abſolute, where a ſingle paper ſigned under the Kings hand hath the ſame efficacy as an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>England:</hi> and in order to this, you muſt expect that his mercenary Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers muſt and would be remembred: If you demand in what; I anſwer, with the whole plunder of <hi>London,</hi> as the readieſt means to give them all content for their ſervice; and if this ſeem ſtrange to you, I pray call to minde, that in the late Kings time when no occaſion of wars or raiſing of Armies in any reaſon were neceſſary to be levied, but ſuch as our late Grandees, the Earl of <hi>Strafford, Canterbury</hi> and <hi>Cottington</hi> would have to be raiſed againſt the <hi>Scots;</hi> that Earl ſpake it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119898:23"/> openly at the Councel-Table 1640, and to no other man then the Lord Mayor Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Garway,</hi> and others of the Aldermen upon their refuſing to lend the king 100000 <hi>l.</hi> for the <hi>Scotch</hi> War; <hi>It will never do well,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>till the King hangs half a dozen of you Aldermen, and then put the whole City to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome:</hi> Which was proved againſt him at his Arraignment; neither did the king forbear the ſeizing of the Mint for ſupply of that needleſs War: ſo that 'tis evident when Princes have power, they will make no ſcruple to act any thing that conduceth to their deſigns, or to take all things where they can finde it, as 'tis well known he did in the late barbarous War; neither will it be impertinent to put you in remembrance of another inſtance of this kinde, when at or before the beginning of the War, the king took his journey towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army in their march home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards 1641, where he dealt with the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Commanders to turn head on the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in reward whereof they ſhould have the plunder of <hi>London,</hi> with Jewels for ſecurity; an overture which ſome of them were not ſo diſhoneſt as to conceal, but gave notice thereof to the City and their own Commiſſioners then here reſiding: Now, if you farther demand, What the preſent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119898:24"/> Pretender would do in the pre-ſuppoſed caſe, I ſhall again anſwer you, that in reaſon of State (which with Kings and Conquerors hath an <note place="margin">Of the miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that will befal the Nation, eſpecially the City of <hi>London,</hi> in caſe the <hi>Scots</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender comes in by the ſword.</note> immenſe latitude) he would and could do no leſs, then to take preſent order for the ſatisfaction of his Country-men the <hi>Scots,</hi> as alſo for gratifying the proſcribed and fugitive Lords, Cavaleers, both <hi>Engliſh, Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> which firſt took part with his Father, and in this ſuppoſed Conqueſt, joyn'd in ayd of himſelf; ſo that the eſtates of the Parliament Members would be much with the leaſt to make them all compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their ſervices and loſſes ſuſtained by Seiſures, Sequeſtrations, &amp; many total Confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; nay, you may reſt aſſured, that there would follow upon ſuch a Conqueſt, a more exact and rigorous ſearch for Delinquents eſtates againſt the king, then ever the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made for Delinquents againſt them; and you may build upon't, that not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldier, whether Native or Stranger, but would preſs the king for ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able recompence for his ſervice; Inſomuch that there would neceſſarily fall out ſuch a ſtrange change of affairs, and ſo much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the people above that which we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119898:24"/> now ſuffer, as that it would amaze the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal people to look upon the miſeries which would befal them; neither ought you to eſteem of that ridiculous ſurmiſe of Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> annexed to the concluſion of all his jugling fragments, to wit, that the late kings Act of Oblivion would have been the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and onely way both to reconcile all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and (as he infers) ſettle peace throughout all the three kingdoms, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſubtil kinde of begging the Queſtion, and onely for his own private ends, having a tacite relation to himſelf, though craftily umbrated under the vail of the common good, and in a cunningneſs to endeer the Souldery to him, with a ſuper-indulgent ſeemingly
<note place="margin">Of the juglings of Judge <hi>Jenkins in Lex terrae.</hi>
                  </note> care he pretended to have them paid by all means; when the crafty fox only intended his own indemnity, in freeing himſelf of all debts, acompts and moneys, truſted in his hands, and for many years moſt unjuſtly detained from the right owners <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> by name of the county of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
                  </note>; you may take it in the next de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of an article of your faith, that the king com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in (by the way of the ſword) cannot (for the reaſons alledged) be ſo prodigal of his grace, as to ſpend ſo laviſhly on the ſtock
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119898:25"/> of his new gotten Conqueſt, to grant a piece of an Act of Oblivion; for farther proof whereof, I pray remember, that when the late king, after the battel at <hi>Edge-hil,</hi> fortified <hi>Oxford,</hi> and as then (to moſt mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) was in a ſairer way to carry all before him, there was not any debate in that mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gril Parliament (as the king in his Letters to the Queen calls them) that pleaſed him, and glad he was to be rid of the tumultuous mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there made unto him; for even that Conventicle compoſed of the Fugitive Members of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (plotted by himſelf) had not the right meaſure of his foor, but in a confuſed and ſtreperous manner fell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways athawrt his inclinations, which were ſecrets he meant not to diſcover but to ſuch as could gueſs at them, and comply with his deſigns before himſelf came to diſcloſe them; and ſuch as had that faculty, were the beſt inſtruments for his turn; and believe it Gentlemen, he was too dark and cunning a Prince for any that he ever imployed; &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, could he then, or at any other time have deſtroyed this Parliament, he would have altered the Government, and hanged by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees moſt, if not all the Members, together with all their adherents, and conſequently to have made uſe of their eſtates as the exegency of his affairs then required, to gratifie
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119898:25"/> ſuch of the Nobility and Gentry as he had befool'd in, to ſide with him, though to their own loſs, and that of the univerſal Nation, and this was well known to all men of an ounce of wit, that made any reſort to his <hi>Oxford</hi> Garriſon, as it hath been openly confeſt by ſome of his chiefeſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note n="*" place="margin">Colonel <hi>Leg</hi> and others.</note>, and of greateſt truſt about his perſon, ſince the rendition of that City, and in this particular I appeal to you Colonel, who then waited on his Majeſty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Colonel.</speaker>
               <p>That which you now avouch <hi>Patriotus,</hi> is a known truth, and the king in reaſon of State, and in reference to his own profit, and the deſigns he had in hand, as alſo for our ſakes which ſtood to him, would do no leſs then change the <note place="margin">The change of the Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity would follow a Conqueſt.</note> Laws and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but eſpecially to quit himſelf of all Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which throughout moſt Raigns have been ſo croſs and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to their kings; and so to any Act of Oblivion after a Conqueſt obtained, and that then a general pardon ſhould have been granted to all ſides; the Judge was out of his ſphear and pratled like a Parrot; for admit that the king ſhould ſo much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhute himſelf, as to grant an Act of Oblivion,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119898:26"/> in what a condition ſhould we of the Souldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be? what then could we expect in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of our ſervice, (which for his late Majeſties ſake and the Kings that now is, or ſhall be in ſpight of the Devil) have haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded our lives and fortunes? Sure I am, my late Maſter, not onely promiſed me, but granted to divers of us his Commanders, ſuch and ſuch Parliament mens eſtates; yea, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs Colonel <hi>Gunters</hi> eſtate of the County of <hi>Pembrook,</hi> and divers others.</note> Delinquents, both Lands and Goods; and you may be ſure, more he would have given had he obtained his ends, then all of you are aware of; and I doubt not, but that his Royal Succeſſor in good time will do the ſame as his Father intended, ſo ſoon as he comes to be inveſted with the Septer; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he would be the moſt ungrateful Prince, moſt deficient and wanting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that ever was in the world? Nay, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perſwades me <hi>Patriotus</hi> to concur with your opinion, as touching this treacherous City of <hi>London,</hi> from whence the Parliament in the very beginning of the War had their only aſſiſtance, and were firſt enabled to wage War with their King, which I hope his now Majeſtie will never forget, whenſoever he comes to be Enthroned, and then I doubt not, but to have a good ſhane of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119898:26"/> Citizens money, Gold Chains, Rings, Plate, Jewels, Silks, Satins, Velvets,
<note place="margin">Of the implacable batre: the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers bear to the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> and that in plentiful meaſure, ſince I have taken ſpecial notice that they bequeathed not all their Riches to the Parliament; ſome I am ſure, and that good ſtore, are left for ſuch as better deſerves them, then ſuch Mecanicks as knew not how otherwiſe to uſe their goods, then to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his Majeſty and the Kingdoms detriment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Colonel, I profeſs I am bound to honour you, for that you have candidly and like your ſelf ſpoken the truth, and what in reaſon (in ſuch a caſe) would befall the City, not onely in the total plunder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which will be much, with the leaſt to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſuch a multitude, both of Natives and Strangers; neither can it ſink into my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that the ranſacking of the City will be the worſt that may befall it; ſuch an implacable hatred do you of the old Cavalry in general bear towards the Citizens, that if God ave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t it not, in all probability the whole City will run the ſame fortune with <hi>Sagun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in <hi>Spain, Carthage</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> and <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and this fate the Cavaleers themſelves have often in my hearing wiſht unto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119898:27"/>Neut.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, your divinations ſeem ſtrange to me, and they very much trouble my cogitations to hear you talk in ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid language; I hope you believe the King of <hi>Scots</hi> to be a Chriſtian, and not that he will deſtroy himſelf, which will be as good as done, whenſoever ſo great and oppulent a City becomes ruined, which is the key of the Kingdom, and from whence iſſues the greateſt Revenue and Income the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have ever received by Cuſtoms and Impoſts from the Merchants; but more eſpecially, ſince he cannot be ignorant that he hath within this City a world of loyal Subjects, (as I my ſelf for one) which never bore arms againſt his Father, nor voluntarily contributed to the Parliament one groat, otherwiſe then needs he muſt whom the Devil drives; therefore I doubt not, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the game goes, he will remember his friends, and diſtinguiſh them from his foes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Excellently well infer'd <hi>Neutralis,</hi> it ſeems then you conceive your ſelf ſafe and ſure, for that in all the late Wars you have carried your ſelf in a neutral way, &amp; according to the old adage, <hi>bene vivit qui bene la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit,</hi> he fares beſt that keeps himſelf cloſe and out of the ſcuffle. But ſuppoſe the King after his Victory and march, comes to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119898:27"/> be poſſeſt of the City, accompanied (as that you may believe) with four or five ſeveral Nations, can you imagine that ſo numerous an Army attending his perſon, will or can Quarter elſwhere then in the City, and when they are there, think you not but that the Souldier will have a minde to the buſineſs, <hi>viz,</hi> to take <note place="margin">A continued deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effects that will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beſal the Nation in the caſe aforeſaid.</note> up their pay out of the ranſacking of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and that without any diſtinction of perſons? haply you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the King out of his Grace and good will towards his friends, will cauſe a mark, or ſome croſs to be ſet up at their doors, whereby to difference his loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from thoſe which aſſiſted the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and took up Arms againſt him and his Father. No <hi>Neutralis,</hi> let not ſuch a <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera</hi> enter in your thoughts, when you ſhall finde your imagined croſs to be no other then in ſo promiſcuous a plundring, that your ſelf or any others of your mode ſhall eſcape ſcot-free, or that whenſoever the Souldierie falls to riffling, think you, any of them will be ſo nice and mannerly, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear any that lies in the way of their fury, or that in ſuch a confuſion, the King himſelf (were he willing) can ſtay them, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand are prompted to enr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119898:28"/> with a booty, which lies ſo readily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, or that the Souldier will be ſo modeſt as to omit ſo fair an opportunity, and ſuffer the Citizens to convey their caſh and commoditities out of the way of their needy, and greedy clutches: Let me I beſeech you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute this caſe a little farther with you, for reſt aſſured, that not onely thoſe which had a hand in his Fathers death, (whom long ſince he hath doom'd to death and confiſcation by his own D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clarations) but even all thoſe which aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted the Parliament, or ſtood neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, will neceſſarily ſall into the number of plundred perſons, yea all ſuch as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the War took up Arms, and were liſted under the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> (which indeed were the firſt that broke the Ice, and made the way open to the new Model under the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and the now Lord General <hi>Cromwel;)</hi> Do you think that any of thoſe of the firſt eſtabliſhment, which laid down Arms when the Lord General <hi>Eſſex</hi> layd down his Commiſſion, divers of which, either before or after have been choſen Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Members: and were known to be bold ſpeakers in the behalf of the late Kings re-admiſſion to the Kingly Government, will or can eſcape? If you conceive they will, your imagination is vain and reaſonleſs, ſince it ſtands not with reaſon of State, or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119898:28"/> the Kings neceſſities to loſe the leaſt griſt that otherwiſe may come to his wanting Mill: Moreover, you may be ſure on't, that in order to all the premiſed plundrings and confiſcations, you ſhall finde all rich men, or ſo accounted, will be cal'd to an after recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and holes pickt in their coats (of what party ſoever they have been) to the end to ſupply the Kings great debts and urgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; for who knows not, but that he hath borrowed much, and yet wants more then can well be <note place="margin">Of the fearful conſequences that attend a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> imagined, and that having the ſword in his hand, he will and muſt have money whereſoever it is to be had; and then believe it, the next bout will be a ſtrict inquiſition, whom they are or have been, which have taken the old Covenant, and the new Engagement, or have bought any of the Crown-Land;, or goods of the late Kings, the Biſhops &amp; Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents eſtates; and in order to this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, a rigorous inquiry will of cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe fall in, who they are which the Parliament hath employed, as actors and inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uments for the promoting of their deſigns, whether in the City or elſewhere in the Country; neither may you doubt on'c, but that all the Judges, Serjeants at Law, Officers, Clerks of the Crown and Chancery, Sheriffs, Juſtices
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119898:29"/> of peace, Commiſſioners, Committees, with all other inferior Clerks and Officers, whom the Parliament have employed throughout the Nation, acting by, and under their power, will by degrees be fetcht over and enforc't to come off with greater Fines then poſſibly they are able to bear, and this (in part) was put in practiſe by the late Kings Commiſſions thoughout all his Quarters, and whereſoever his Armies had prevalence, when he reſided at <hi>Oxford</hi> and elſwhere; and enough there will be, which will not fail to inſtruct and inform this King, that all the riches of the Land, (ſaved from the ſpoyl of his Father) will not be ſufficient to make him ſatisfaction for the infinite loſſes which the Crown hath ſuſtained ſince the beginning of the late War, and to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence ſuch as have ſuffered by taking his part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>Signiour <hi>Patriotus,</hi> dam me, if all that you have now ſaid be not Oracles; and the King ought not, or can in honour do leſs then that which with well meaſured reaſon you have declared, and in caſe he doth it not to a hairs breadth, I ſhall take him not to be ſo wiſe as he ſhould be; for in confirmation of your opinion, Ile tell you a ſtory, and 'tis a true one, on my life, and the reputation of a Souldier, that all of us at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119898:29"/> 
                  <hi>Oxford</hi> concluded <note n="*" place="margin">This is a known truth, and hath been often aver'd by many reſiding at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1642. when to all mens think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng the King was in a ſairer way to have carried all before him.</note> that after the deſtruction of the Parliament, the King un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly was reſolved both to alter the Laws and change the Government, hang all the Parliament men at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for high Treaſon, and then baniſh all the <hi>Puritans</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and next the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was, to take the ſame cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (as the greateſt Enemies to Monarchy and Epiſcopacy in the World;) and if ever the King comes to be Maſter, and in the way, wherein I doubt not but he ſhall be with the ſword in his hand, and we of the Cavalry at his heels, if he hangs not ten thouſand of theſe <hi>Puritans, Independants</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> I ſhall for ever hereafter judge him uncapable of the managery of any other Scepter, then that of a ſweetch or an hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt riding rod; and be confident Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lemen of the truth of this Story, in confirmation whereof I remember, that my Maſter commiſſioned the chief Juſtice <hi>Heath,</hi> the Atturney <hi>Harbert,</hi> with divers more of our Lawyers at <hi>Oxford,</hi> to go in their Circuits (as I remember they cal'd their Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer)</hi> with Authority to hang all thoſe (as they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119898:30"/> well deſerved) of the Parliaments party, but a pox take them, they were ſo much afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with us of his Majeſties party, that the King was compeld to
<note n="*" place="margin">The reaſons of the late Kings withdrawing of his commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer.</hi>
                  </note> retract his Commiſſions, for ſaving of ſuch of his own party, then in the Parliaments cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody; though one <hi>Francklin,</hi> whom I took priſoner at <hi>Marleborough,</hi> and one Sir <hi>Hugh Owins,</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſs of <hi>Haverford</hi>-Weſt, both Parliament Members; the firſt whereof indeed dyed in priſon at <hi>Oxford</hi> before his Tryal, but as to the other, I well remember he was deſign'd by the King himſelf to be tryed in his own Country, and for High Treaſon; however, as afterward I heard, he eſcaped the halter, but no otherwiſe then for the reaſons before told you; moreover, I am confident, that if his Majeſty that now is comes once to ride on the fore-horſe, he will not fail to make ſure work with all <note n="*" place="margin">The late Kings deſign to quit himſelf of all Parliaments.</note> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or Succeſſors ſhall ſtand in fear to be farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled by them, or made ſlaves to their Subjects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, you have all ſpoken according to your fancies and affections; ſure I am, 'tis very fit that reſtitution ſhould
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119898:30"/> be made, where eſtates have been been injuriouſly taken from the right Owners, and ſervices rewarded by him for whoſe uſe and benefit they were performed; and 'tis Divinity, <hi>That the Labourer is worthy of his hire:</hi> but in caſe the King cannot come to his own other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by the ſword, I ſay, that ſuch as ſhall aſſiſt and enable him to obtain that which no man can deny to be rightſully his own, ought in all equity to be recompenc't by ſome means or other, for as the preſent condition of the King now ſtands, I ſee no other means left him, but by ſeiſure of the Parliaments eſtates, and plunder of the City, from whom my late innocent Maſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his bane, and the Parliament the means both to furniſh and maintain an Army againſt him at an inſtant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Pardon me good Doctor, ſince I perceive you ſomewhat miſtake me, for I ſay not, that in caſe the King comes in by the ſword, he then ought to ranſack the City, but that of neceſſity he will be compel'd to do it, otherwiſe the Souldiers will of courle do it of themſelves; ſince 'tis well known to be the deſign of the Royal party both at home and abroad, to be revenged on the Citizens whenſoever opportunity ſerves them; for 'tis confeſt on all hands, that in the beginning of the War, they voluntarily
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119898:31"/> came in with their moneys, jewels, and plate, and truſted it on the publick Faith, without which, on an inſtant the Parliament could not poſſibly raiſe and pay ſuch an Army as they did; and there is no doubt on't, that in caſe the King ſhall make ſcruple to plunder the City, yet am I confident he ſhall be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſt and invited to do it, or at leaſt to impoſe ſuch a ranſome on it, as the Citizens ſhall never be able to undergo; but God forbid either of them ſhould be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>Patriotus,</hi> I perceive your meaning, but what you would not ſhould be put in execution, reſt aſſured, If I can help it on, it ſhall not be left undone; and I farther ſay, that in caſe any ſuch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſhall be offered, God forbid it ſhould be omitted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Neut.</speaker>
               <p>And I am glad, Colonel, I know your good meaning towards the City, but I hope God will ſo provide for us (as hitherto he hath done) that as yet we have not taſted of thoſe cruelties which you of the Kings party have committed in ſeveral parts of the Land, whereby you have made the Kings memory odious to the preſent times and future; ſo I doubt not but the ſame God will preſerve and defend us from your malice: But I beſeech you <hi>Patriotus,</hi> may
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119898:31"/> there not ſome way or other be thought upon to admit of his Majeſty (who now is) on ſafe and honourable terms, and ſuch as may ſute with the ſecurity of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, in my poor judgement, as the late King, and preſent Pretender hath handled the matter, there are no hopes left to any of that Family, by a peaceable way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inveſt themſelves with the Regal Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but onely that of the ſword, and then I have already told you in plain Engliſh, what in all probability will be the ſad iſſues; either continual attempts made on the preſent power by the Pretender, or a perpetual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of war, ſo long as any of the Family and diſſendants of King <note n="*" place="margin">King <hi>James</hi> the firſt plotter of abſolute ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, &amp; projector to diſſolve &amp; deſtroy Parliaments, and this deſign farthered by the Prelates.</note> 
                  <hi>James</hi> remain alive; who to ſpeak the truth, lead the way to all our miſeries and concuſſions both in the Church and State, and his Succeſſor purſuing his principles, what through his own inclinations to abſolute Soveraignty, the Queens Mother and her Daughters Councels, furthered by the Biſhops and other corrupt inſtruments, ſo brought it about, both to his own ruine, and the diſ-inheriting of the preſent Pretender; ſo fatal a thing it is,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119898:32"/> when Princes will be more then of right they ſhould be, and will not remember that they are no otherwiſe to govern their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed to their tuition, but by the ſame Rules, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> in vita Reg. Johannis.</note> Laws, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as at their firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs they received their Crowns on Oath; and when the Grand father and Son ſhall forget their own Engagements, and recede from their own principles, <hi>viz.</hi> that if <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con Doron.</note> Kings would but conſider that they are ordained of God for the good and benefit of their people, and not their Subjects deſtinated to be governed by their own will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they ſhould then never ſtray out of the right Orbe of Government: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over 'tis moſt true, that the Grandchild and preſent Pretender, neither in the beginning of the wars nor ſince, took the right way to gain the love and acceptance of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and people, but in his open pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luance of hoſtility both by Sea and Land incenſed them, and made himſelf utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of acceptance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>For Gods love, What would you that the poor innocent Prince ſhould have done on the maſſacre of his Father, and when all of his undeniable rights, (divolved on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119898:32"/> him) were taken from him, and no means left him whereby to eat bread, otherwiſe then to beg or borrow it, and you know he cannot (Camelion-like) live by the ayr.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, 'tis of too tranſcendent a nature for me to direct Princes diſpoſſeſt, or rather forfeiting of their Patrimonies by Tyranny, what courſe to take for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; but you cannot forget how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily he was ſet on and engaged in his Fathers quarrel, which had he not been, but in ſuch a conteſt born himſelf in a neutral way, or ſate ſtill as his couſin the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> did, I cannot diſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> any reaſon why the Parliament ſhould have excluded him, but rather admitted him, as the States formerly did <hi>Edward</hi> the Third after his Fathers depoſition; but alaſs, he was ſo much, &amp; ſo far intereſſed in the quarrel, both in his Fathers life time; and more unhappily ſince ſhewed
<note place="margin">The reaſons of the Parliaments excluding the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> and the reſt of the Deſcendants of King <hi>James.</hi>
                  </note> himſelf the Son of that Father, from whom he received all thoſe deſtructive principles of Tyranny, which have ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undone all thoſe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes that purſued them, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of King <hi>John, Edward,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, manifeſtly demonſtrates; ſome of his Commiſſions iſſued out in his Fathers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119898:33"/> life time whilſt he was a Priſoner I have heard of, which ſhews him not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>indulgent towards Parliaments; but to this, doubtleſs an utter Enemy, and to ſpeak the truth, he took not the right way to win the hearts of the people, ſince 'tis evident, that he hath granted ſundry Commiſſions, to rob and ſpoyl the Merchants at Sea, <hi>viz.</hi> to his couſin <hi>Rupert</hi> and his brother <hi>Maurice,</hi> as his Father not long before Commiſſioned both the ſaid Princes to ſpoyl and plunder the poor people by Land; more may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, which ſhall rather be concealed then ript up by me; onely in a word more to you Colonel, and all of your party, whom I could wiſh to look about you, and bethink your ſelves of the ſad iſſues, which (in ſuch a change as we have preſuppoſed) will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily befal your ſelves and poſterity; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily the King during his own time, and to ſome few of you may carry a favourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, but that his Succeſſors or himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to beſtow Charters of Immunities upon you all, and intail them on your Heirs-males, is a very vain and idle imagination; for after a Conqueſt, and not unlikely within a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters time of a Century, it will of courſe fall out as it did with <hi>Jacobs</hi> Poſterity upon the deceaſe of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> when his Succeſſor would not ſo much as look upon, or know
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119898:33"/> 
                  <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but his whole raſe and Poſterity fell altogether into the common-ſhore of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and Slavery; And yet, ſuch is your infatuation like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which cryed for a King, and ſoon after would have been quit of him, but God told them he would not hear them; and indeed few there are amongſt us all that judge aright, or know our own happineſs and freedom in this preſent change of the Government.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Neut.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patriotus,</hi> Give me leave in a word or two to interpoſe; It appears to me, as by your diſcouſe I have collected, that our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the preſent power of ſome ſpecial ſelected Gentry, without King and the late priviledged Lords, (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch I confeſs were wont to do what they liſted) will be more ſafe, honourable, and profitable for the people, notwithſtanding our Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then ſuch as neceſſarily will befal us, ſhould the excluded King come in by force of Arms; I profeſs in ſuch a caſe, I know not which ſide to take with ſafety; adviſe me to the beſt, and I'le thank you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neutralis,</hi> I perceive you to be a crafty fox; you are beſt able to judge what party to incline to; I leave you to your own choyce, whether to ſide with the preſent power (in caſe of an invaſion) or to aſſiſt the <hi>Scotch</hi> King; for I finde 'tis your own
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119898:34"/> ſafety, not the common good, that you aym at; onely this, take heed that reaſon do not invade you before it perſwades you, though it be already both ſufficiently inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and proved, that your adherence to the preſent eſtabliſhment will be your beſt courſe, yea, on any Invaſion of the <hi>Scotch</hi> King, to fight for your liberty, and not ſit ſtill as you ſay you have done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patriotus,</hi> In all our conference hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereto, we have omitted the principal verb which governs the ſentence, and that is, concerning the late Parliaments ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> acting according to their own wils and pleaſures; what they Vote, was without any more adoe Enacted for Law, as a Rule to the univerſal Nation; right or wrong, it muſt be obeyed; Now whether 160 at moſt, of 560 at leaſt, which formerly ſate in both houſes could be a Parliament, is the Quere. I pray reſolve me in this point; for in Law, or in any rational mans judgement, a <note n="*" place="margin">The grand obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Royal party anſwered in the next Reply.</note> Parliament they could not be, but rather an uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patious and deſpotical number backt by an Army; therefore I ſay, ſpeak your own conſcience, what you conceive them to have been, without King, Lords, Biſhops, and the major part of the Commons, all ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119898:34"/> by the Kings Writ, and choſen by their ſeveral Countries, and violently pul'd out of the houſe by the Souldiers for diſſenting to the Votes of no more addreſſes, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder being ſo few, that in any reaſon they could not ſo much as pretend to be a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, much leſs the Repreſentative of the univerſal people; yet had they the confidence that whatſoever they Enacted, to aſſume it to be done in the name of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> which is one of the ſtrangeſt pieces of Non-ſence that ever was heard of in the World; you may call to minde what became of thoſe thirty Tyrants at <hi>Athens;</hi> the parallel is not at a very wide diſtance; therefore before we depart, I beſeech you deliver your opinion for the better ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my conſcience, and tell me how it came to paſs that none or very few of the Lords ſate there with the Commons, which till of later times, never were admitted to ſit with them, neither cal'd to ſit by them; for all our ancient Parliaments were onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of King, Biſhops, Abbots, Earls and Barons, without the ſcum of the Vulgar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, 'tis moſt true, that upon the firſt view, that remnant which ſo lately ſate at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in moſt mens underſtanding, ſeemed to be no other then an uſurped
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119898:35"/> power, and theſe back't by the Souldier; but when we come to the Examination of their mutilation, and how their number came to be diminiſhed you will be of another minde; for as the Author of the Kings Life and Raign exactly lays it down, and reſolves this doubt, and tells you by whom it was firſt lamed and diſordered, this we all know, that it was at firſt legally ſummoned by the Kings Writ, with Lords, Biſhops, and Commons, which by your favour are not the ſcum of the people, but as good Gentlemen as any of the Lords; but as afterwards it fell out by the Kings practiſes and artifices, it was firſt leſſned in both Houſes, near to a moity, to make up his Mungril Parliament at <hi>Oxford;</hi> and yet the King himſelf and that Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, both calls them and acknowledges theſe at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to be a Parliament, though much againſt his will; <note place="margin">The late reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k of the old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though lamed and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened by the late King.</note> and 'tis a plain caſe, that ſince the excluſion of another par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the Souldier, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder or relick was ſtill the Parliament, and ſtood upon the ſame feet, as 'twas firſt ſummoned 3 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1640. with their full number; and that piece of a Parliament left as you call them, acted by the ſame power; ſo that you muſt always take Powers in their preſent being, not as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119898:35"/> they have been, when inforc't from their old preſidents and uſages, which I finde not to have been always one and of the ſame form, but varied in all Ages, according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of times and accidents; for without all queſtion, that <hi>Magnum Conſilium</hi> or <hi>Commune Conſilium,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> calls it, of the old <hi>Britons,</hi> was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <note place="margin">Caeſa. Com. lib. 5.</note> of the ſelf-ſame form with the <hi>Witenagomots</hi> of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> neither thoſe with the Parliaments as they were after called on the coming in of the <hi>Normans;</hi> and ſince the Conqueſt, we finde them very much to vary; <note place="margin">Parliaments throughout all Ages not one &amp; the ſame in form, though in ſubſtance; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any Record ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, that ſhews the time when the late form, with King, Lords Spiritual and Temporal, with the Commons, had its inſtitution; but doubleſs 'tis both a new and falſe aſſertion, that the Commons had not their free voyce from the firſt foundation of Parliaments to this preſent, as it evindently appears by the citations within mentioned, which are authentick and incontradictable.</note> as for inſtance, <hi>Quarto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtoris, Rex fecit ſummon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri per univerſos conſulatus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glos nobiles, &amp; ſapientes, &amp; ſua lege eruditos, ut eorum jura &amp; conſuetudines ab ipſis audiret:</hi> the fourth year of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, the King cauſed to be ſummoned out of every Country of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> all the Nobility, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119898:36"/> wiſe men, and all ſuch as were Learned in the Laws, to the end that he might hear and underſtand, what their Laws and cuſtoms were. <hi>Hoved, lib. de Litchfield;</hi> Moreover, <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. <hi>apud fontem Clericorum fecit ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneri omnes Arch-Epiſ. Epiſcopos, Abbates, omnes nobiles Angliae, &amp; ſapientes, &amp; omnes incolas Regni;</hi> The King cauſed a ſummons go <hi>Clerkenwel,</hi> of all the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, all the Nobles, Wiſe men, and all the Inhabitants, or as I conceive, by <hi>(Incolas)</hi> the chief dwellers in the Kingdom, which ſeems to be a multitudinous Aſlembly. <hi>Math. Paris, Edm. de Loud.</hi> Again, <hi>Hov.</hi> 2. <hi>decimo Reg. praeſentibus Arch-Epiſ. Epiſcopis, Abbattibus, Prio. Comitibus &amp; proceribus Regni. Math Paris:</hi> But <hi>Hoveden &amp; Fitz-Steven,</hi> make mention of <hi>Clerus &amp; Populus,</hi> the Clergy and People to be then aſſembled; the tenth of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Earls and Barons, together with the Clergy and people. <hi>Paris</hi> calls this Aſſembly <hi>Generale Conſilium,</hi> a General Councel; Now amongſt many other preſidents, I ſhall only inſtance in one or two more, <hi>viz. Sexto Ioban.</hi> at <hi>Oxford, Communi conſenſu Arch-Epiſ. Epiſcoporum, Comitum, Baronum, &amp; omnium fidelium noſtrorum Angliae;</hi> by the common conſent of Arch-biſhops, Biſhops,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119898:36"/> Earls, Barons, &amp; all our faithful men of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Parl. Rot. pat.</hi> 5. &amp; there are ſome preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which only mention <hi>Barones &amp; libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros bomines totius Regni,</hi> onely the Barons and all the free-men of the Realm; <hi>tempore Henrici</hi> 3. and another of this reign, and before the Grant of the great Charter, hath it, <hi>Convocatum eſt Londoniis, praeſidente Arch-Epiſ. cum toto Clero &amp; tota Sect a Laical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> An Aſſembly at <hi>London,</hi> the Arch-biſhops being Preſident with all their Clergy and all the Laicks, without any mention of Earls, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, or Biſhops. <hi>Auth. Eulog.</hi> which ſeems to be a ſtrange kinde of Parliament; ſo that in an hundred more of Preſidents which may be inſtanced, it will manifeſtly appear, that our antient Parliaments though they are acknowledged for a National meeting, made and un-made Laws according to the viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of times; yet were they not always of one conſtant and ſet form, though tending to no other, and the ſelf-ſame end <hi>(ſalus populi)</hi> the ſafety and conſervation of the people, by their Enacting ſuch Laws as then were thought fit to be eſtabliſhed for the common welfare of the Nation, to which all our Laws and Statutes in the ſame words have ſpecial reference, though, 'tis confeſt in ancient times, often varied in the form, but never from the end; And 'tis very obſervable
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119898:37"/> that neither the ancient ſummons to our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments were always of one ſtamp, but varied in <note place="margin">Neither that the ſummons to our Parliaments, are of one and the ſelf ſame form.</note> moſt our Kings Raigns; ſure we are, that laſt of the kings was much different from thoſe of old, which ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more had in them inſerted, <hi>viz. ad tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, conſulendum &amp; ordinandum cum nobis, &amp;c.</hi> the principle Gerund <hi>(Ordinandum)</hi> being purpoſely omitted, leaſt it might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate a greater power in the Commons to act by, then the King was willing they ſhould have; juſt in the ſame manner as the Archbiſhop curtald the moſt material clauſe of the Kings Coronation Oath, that ſo he might aſſume to himſelf a greater power then of right belonged unto him; but this is a ſubject which to diſpute to the full, would take up more time then we can at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent well ſpare; onely in a word, that the Commons ſate not in our ancient Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that now they onely ſit there, where the King and Lords ſate alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; Truly Doctor, I retract not from that which I have often ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> that theſe late times have produced ſuch Monſters of men, ſuch Traytors and ſhameleſs Vipers that have endevoured to blot out of memory thoſe ancient Rights and Liberties which the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119898:37"/> Natives have for ſo many hundred years en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, and to devour the mother that bare them, moſt unnaturally attempting to enſlave themſelves and their Poſterity: I ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly name ſome of them. Judge <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> Book.</note> 
                  <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and another, under the name of Mr <hi>Prynne,</hi> which have avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Commons were not ſummoned or ſate in our ancient Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: which is a moſt imputent lye and falſe aſſertion, as it evidently appears by thoſe old authentick Authorities even now recited; and indeed, I have ſpent many an hour in a diligent ſearch into Antiquities, to finde out the time when our late form of King Lords, and Biſhops, with the Commons, all call'd by Writ from their reſpective Burroughs, had its beginning; though it may be enough, to ſatisfie rational men, that it hath been at leaſt of 500 years ſtanding if not 600, as by <note n="*" place="margin">Archyton.</note> Mr <hi>Lambert</hi> and many other better Authors, and far better ſeen in the Laws, then that falſe Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> ever was it manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears. Doctor, to put a period to this particular, let me tell you, for your own and the better ſatisfaction of thouſands more of your opinion, that new powers will have new Laws, new Forms; and we of the people muſt and ought to obey them or ſmart for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119898:38"/> our diſobedience; and ſo would the King have had, (you ſhould have found it too true) had he prevailed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs indeed, you have given me full ſatisfaction, as well to my firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether that relick of the late Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament was a legal Parliament, as to my laſt concerning the ſitting of the Commons in our Antient Parliament; but what ſay you to this new form, that meerly is ſummoned by the power of the Souldiery, and almoſt half Souldiers that now ſit at <hi>Weſtminſter?</hi> by what right of a legal Election do they ſit as a Parliament? for by the Law and right of the people they were to have made choyce of their own Repreſentative?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>By the right of the ſword, which in all Ages hath been the original foundation of all Laws and Powers; and where that weapon hath predominance, we muſt not altogether inſiſt upon Law; for <hi>ſilent leges inter arma,</hi> but look upon Gods Providence with the effects which this power may produce in the iſſue for the good of the univerſal Nation, ſince that after the States Army (by Gods great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) had no ſooner freed the people from farther bloodſhed and rapine, the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament being at eaſe and not playing their parts ſo dexterouſly as they might have done,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119898:38"/> but minding their own intereſts more then that of the publick, 'twas thought fit by the Councel of war, to put a period to their fruitleſs ſitting, as formerly they did to the Kings exorbitant Government, and for his often breaches of Faith with God, and his truſt with the whole Nation, over whom he was appointed to rule by the Laws of the Land, and not by his own will and pleaſure; for <hi>bonus paſtor ponit vitam pro ovibus,</hi> the good Shepherd lays down his life for his ſheep, he never flayes or deſtroys them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>I hope Sir, you cannot ſay (as your intimation imports) the King my late bleſſed Maſter was ever known to flay his Subjects you'l never leave the Round-head lyes and ſlanders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>No Sir, I do not poſitively ſay ſo, or that the King was guilty of pulling his Subjects skins over their heads, as S. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmew</hi> is reported to have been ſerved by his cruel Perſecutors; but by your favor, ſince you are ſo captious and uncivil to aſperſe me with lying and ſlandring, as that you can do when you pleaſe on innocent children, and then make them good with vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of dam-mees, &amp; other fearful Oathes and imprecations, 'tis well known that before the king levied war againſt the beſt Subjects
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119898:39"/> he had, ſome have had their ears cut off by the roots, their bodies whipt all over in gore blood, and their fore-heads branded with hot Irons, no man knows well for what, more then to pleaſe the great Arch-Prelate, who would have it ſo; and the Lords of the Star-Chamber, and others of the High Inquiſition, could do no leſs or durſt do no other then vote as he would have them; and as ſure it is, that you and your Complices under the Kings Commiſſions, kill'd, plundered and ſhaved the poor innocent people whereſoever you march'c or quartered, which in many places of the Land you perpetrated without mercy; ſo that by your leave, the King himſelf was the ſole Author and cauſe of all the blood and miſeries that beſell the three Nations, as himſelf ſometimes hath confeſt; but good Sir, enough of this; for it grows late, and a time we muſt have to retreat, as you my good Colonel, have had a time to rob, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſpoyl the poor people, though I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, you have not purchaſed any great ſtore of Lands with the remains of your ſtoln goods; but in caſe you have any ſtore left you, there are yet very good peny-worths to be had of Delinquents eſtates, and you may likewiſe buy wood and timber if you have any uſe for it, if not, that you will keep it by you, for ſome other miſchievous pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119898:39"/> and not live quietly and peaceably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the preſent Government, the State you may be ſure on't, will finde out a parcel that may ſerve your turn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Neut.</speaker>
               <p>Colonel, I have often told you, that he would be too hard for you at this kinde of fencing; yet you'l take no warning; do you not underſtand <hi>Patriotus</hi> his meaning, that the State will ſoon finde out a parcel of Timber for you, if you ſtir and foment more miſchief; you may gueſs at his meaning; if not, take it into your ſecond conſideration, that there is an intent of erecting a new Court of Juſtice, which will tell us all our fortunes, in caſe any of us ſhould be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſie and plot new inſurrections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>A pox of him, and the Court of Juſtice to boot, that ever I ſaw or heard of either of them; I pree-thee Doctor, ſuffer not this round-headed-fellow thus to go away with the Bucklers, and to ſend us away like mutes, and with a flie in our ears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>Colonel, to deal plainly, your langnage is inſufferable; at our laſt confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence you gave the firſt offence; and now again, you are at your old lock; for more boldly and uncivilly yon durſt not have ſpoken, when you were in the head of the greateſt Army the King ever had; the truth is,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119898:40"/> you too much forget your ſelf, and think not where you are, and to whom you ſpeak; ſhould I judge of moſt that the Gentleman hath ſaid, I ſhould be a Witneſs my ſelf, that he hath ſpoken truth, and that with well meaſured Reaſon; but I beſeech you <hi>Patrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> pardon the Colonels incivility, and be pleaſ'd to ſatisfie me in ſome particulars, which I ſuppoſe you may do in a few minutes of time; then I ſhall both thank you and wiſh you a good night, and at your better lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhall not fail to give you a friendly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit; Sir, in brief, King <hi>John</hi> was a known Tyrant, an Uſurper, and a murtherer of his own Brothers children, an Enemy to the Clergy, and the greateſt depopulator of the Kingdom that ever before it had; and yet the States and Nobility forget all his Tyrannies &amp; miſdeeds, and after his poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Swinſteed,</hi> admitted of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent young Son, after call'd by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſoon quitted the Land of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> whom before they had call'd in to their aſſiſtance, and to whom moſt of the great Lords had ſworn fealty; In like manner the Parliament, after the depoſiog of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond for his Tyranny, made choyce of his young Son <hi>Edward</hi> the third, who proved a very gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Prince; likewiſe on the Parliaments
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119898:40"/> depoſing of <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, the State made choyſe of his couſin-german <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bulling-brook,</hi> who though not the next in blood, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently an Uſurper as to the right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, yet was he made King by conſent of the Parliament, and he approved himſelf a very wiſe and politick Prince; whence it appears that the Parliaments and Nobility of thoſe times had ever an eye on the next Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, or to ſuch a one of the blood-Royal, as in their judgements they conceived to be moſt capable and fit to undertake the kingly Government, as it may be inſtanced in their Election of <hi>Steven</hi> Earl of <hi>Bulloyn,</hi> in the abſence of <hi>Maude</hi> the Empreſs next in blood; and ſince that, of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Richmon,</hi> after the killing of that Tyrant <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> on theſe premiſes I beſeech you, a little extend your patience, and tell me what you conceive to have been the reaſons, that the late Parliament not only took away the Kings life by a new preſident, and under colour of a legal hearing, to the great regret of the major part of the Nation, but have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rejected the young Prince of mature years, hopeful and able to govern, together with the Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> with all the diſcendents of King <hi>James,</hi> and have changed the Royal Government into a Common-wealth,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119898:41"/> have ſold all the Lands, Honours, Mannors, and Revenues, anciently by right belonging to the Crown, as the proper Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> Now Sir, By what Law of God, man, or reaſon of State, they have attempted on ſo ſtrange an enterpriſe, paſſes my underſtanding; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the excluſion of the poor innocent Princes, goes directly againſt my conſcience; yet if you pleaſe, I ſhall willing hear what you can ſay, for my better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, your queſtions neceſſarily will require a long ſearch into the reaſons wherefore the Parliament enterprized on ſo high a concernment; yet in brief, I ſhall tell you what hath been told me, and by ſome of the late Members on the ſame Queres you have propounded: Firſt, they ſay, that on conſideration of the Kings ſeldom calling, and often diſſolving of ſuch Parliaments as he ſummoned without their due effects, and that for ten years together he refuſed to ſummon any, but ruled (during ſo long an intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) at will and pleaſure, whereby the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt and liberties of the people were ſo much invaded, and ſo many grievances and oppreſſions crept both into the Church and State, that when this late Parliament was (through the extremity of his wants) call'd,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119898:41"/> the Aſſembly was to ſeek where to begin to rectifie and repair the decays of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, which through his own miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, the prodigaltie and diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Court and Clergy had befallen the univerſal Nation, which although he wholly then left to their rectification, yet immediately thereupon he not onely went from his word, and falſified his promiſe, but by the continuance of innumerable practiſes, and his uttermoſt endevors, he ſought nothing more then to obſtruct their Reformation, ruine the Parliament, and put all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into conſuſion, by a moſt bloody and deſtructive war; which the Aſſembly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and that his intent in purſuing his deſigns full ſix years together, and ſo long as he was able, aimed at the utter overthrow of the Laws, and envaſſaladge of the people, and that he had entailed this quarrel on his Son and his Heirs-males in <hi>perpetuum;</hi> how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible then it was for the Parliament to ſettle a firm peace throughout the three Kingdoms, by re-admitting the King full fraught, (though a priſoner) with his wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Principles and deſigns, or to take in any of his Poſterity (afore-hand indoctrinated, in their Fathers frauds and ſubtilties) might amaze the wiſeſt of men, even <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to finde out any other way how to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119898:42"/> free the Nation from pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>petual Tyranny and bloodſhed, but by cutting off both the Father and Son which were ſo deeply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in the controverſie; and to make the ſame uſe of their victories for the future ſecurity and indemnity of the people, as the King himſelf intended to do in the behalf of himſelf and his Succeſſor, had the fortune of a Conqueſt befallen him; thus much in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as to the grounds of the Parliaments reſolution of cutting off the King and his Poſterity; as to the particular reaſons, I pray take them in their order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They alledge, that they had no choyce left them whereby to ſave the Nation from utter ruine, but were by the Law of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity inforc't upon them by the King himſelf and of his own ſeeking both to cut off him and exclude his Poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That having had ſo long patience, and taken ſuch infinite pains during all the wars, (after he had loſt all and was a Priſoner,) to ſatisfie him from time to time, in what poſſibly they could in all things queſtionable between them, and on all his exceptions to reaſon the caſe all along with him in their ſeveral Anſwers and Replies to his Papers, Expreſſes, and Proteſtations, atteſted before God and his Holy Angels, pretending ſtill how really he meant, when by long and ſad
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119898:42"/> experience, they found all his pretences fraudulent; yet could they never ſatisfie him with any Arguments either of Law or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that his own Reaſon, his Will, his Honour, his Conſcience, muſt be the onely Directory to the Parliament, theirs of no eſteem with him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That notwithſtanding their many Addreſſes and humble Petitions preſented unto him (after his cauſleſs receſs from the Parliament) for his return with honor and profit, with this onely reſervation to leave Delinquents to the judgement of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court, they prevailed not, but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended them, and was the skreen to moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Offendors, profeſſing ſtill a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to peace and Treaties (onely to get advantages) when he moſt intended War and Conqueſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That ſuch was the obſtinacy of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural inclination (which himſelf miſcalls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy) from which they found it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to diſſwade him, or yeeld to any (reaſon never ſo well meaſured by them,) but that they muſt yeeld to his, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo unreaſonably preſt by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That in this wilſull purſuance to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his moſt unjuſt ends, he incorrigibly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted to the laſt, without the leaſt reluctation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or acknowledgement, that any fault was in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119898:43"/> himſelf (until he was a Priſoner) but ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more laid all the blame on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That in this long perſiſtance, he had wearied and beggered all his friends and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, at home and abroad, to the deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of three flouriſhing Kingdoms, by the continuation of his Hoſtility, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of a million of poor Innocent ſouls, without any remorſe of ſo much blood ſpilt, more then of one man, his wicked
<note n="*" place="inline">Straford.</note> Inſtrument.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That when he proteſted moſt, and to the height of imprecation, the Parliament at laſt found by the Teſtimony of his own Letters under his hand-writing, that he meant nothing leſs and more contrary, then to his uſual Proteſtations.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That neither all the Honors, Mannors, and Lands of the Crown, or his own blood, (without true repentance) could be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient expiation to God, or recompence to his ſubjects, for the infinite bloodſhed, rapines, and dilapidatins made on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of three Kingdoms.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That ſuch was his inſenſibility of blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that the many Lords, Gentlemen, and infinite others of inferiour quality (ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in his bloody quarrel) he made no other reckoning of them then this, <hi>viz.</hi> that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119898:43"/> they ſuffered no more then of duty they were bound to do for their King, which he avouched on the death of the Earl of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. That thoſe unjuſt pretences which he made, under the notion of his Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, <hi>viz.</hi> the Militia, power of War, Peace, Leagues, Treaties, Array of the people, his negative Voyce in all Parliaments, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of Murderers and Fellons condemned by the Laws of the Land, were all at his only diſpoſure, whereas by the known Laws of the Realm, they have been onely entruſted and conferr'd on our Kings by the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the people in their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, as hereafter ſhall manifeſtly appear.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That all his Treaties with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for peace were perſidious, and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions evermore umbrated under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pecious pretexts, ſubtilties, ſubterſuges, and mental reſervations, as 'twas evident in that at <hi>Colebrook</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by his own Letters to the Duke of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide,</hi> The Kings Letters to the Duke of <hi>Rich. mond,</hi> with others to the Queen.</note> 
                  <hi>Richmond, viz.</hi> Not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to cajole well the <hi>Scots;</hi> and by that at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtring in the Councel-books his calling them a Parliament with mental reſervations, though not <hi>ex animo</hi> ſo acknowledged,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119898:44"/> yet ſummoned by his own Writs, and often ſo eſteemed and call'd by himſelf, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be a legal Parliament by his own mungril Conventicle at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12 That in all his Declarations and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes to the Parliament, he evermore ſeemed to have a tender regard both towards them and the people, when he onely intended his own intereſts with the advance of the Soveraignty to abſoluteneſs by the power of the ſword, and to convey his deſigns to his Succeſſors, as in the inſtance of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide,</hi> One of the Kings Expreſſes, where he yeelds the Militia during his own life, but not ſor his Sons.</note> Militia, is moſt perſpicuous, when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the Parliament would no longer truſt ſo dangerous weapons in his hands.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That ſome of his beſt friends ſuſpected him to be too much verſ't in the <hi>Florentine</hi> Principles, as indoctrinated by a <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> party conſtantly reſident in his own Court, and ſtickled on by the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſions of the Queen-Mother &amp; the Daughter, both which had gained a great intereſt, &amp; had chiefeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on his Concels; and as'tis well known, was wholy governed as the Queen lifted, and at laſt, his inclinations ſo ſtrictly tyed up as that they were not ſubject to any other
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119898:44"/> alteration then as ſhe preſcribed, which was a Rule to whatſoever he undretook.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That he was not wanting to himſelf (for promoting of his arbitrary deſigns) to make uſe of <hi>Machiavels</hi> principle, <hi>Divide &amp; impera,</hi> evermore to ſow diviſions, and to cheriſh any diſſention ariſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parliament and their friends, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ruine them by themſelves.</p>
               <p>Thus Gentlemen, according to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, I have given you an accompt of thoſe Reaſons which have been given me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parliament enterprized on the change of the Government by cutting off the King and his Poſterity, the premiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo true and undenyable, that they ſatisfied me, and prevailed ſo ſar on my belief, that I conceive the Parliament could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe poſſibly have ſecured the Nation from farther ruine; as alſo that their reſolutions therein were directed by the ſpecial hand of God, conſidered together with the and great conſtant charge incident to Monarchy, the often preſſures, and oppreſſions of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject through the Tyranny, ambition, and prodigalitie of moſt of our Kings, the two laſt having beggered and impoveriſhed them moſt of all others, on which conſiderations, the Parliament in reaſon of State, and as the ſtate of the controyerſie then was between
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119898:45"/> them and the King, they found it much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quit themſelves and the people of Regal Government, and to change it into a Republick, as a more ſafe and cheaper Government, rather then any longer to hazard the common liberty on the Rule of any one Prince whatſoever; eſpecially not to truſt thoſe of the <hi>Sotch</hi> Nation; all our Hiſtories and the Parliaments ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence having taught them, that of late years, the Soveraignty by the ambition and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices of both the late Kings was ſtrain'd and tentered up to ſo high a pitch, that it would not ſtoop to a lower power then that of abſoluteneſ.</p>
               <p>Now more particularly to anſwer your Querie as concerning the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the two Dukes, with the reſt of the late Kings loyns; it ſeems likewiſe, that the Parliament knowing them to be the Sons of that father, who had more waſted the Land then all of the <hi>Norman</hi> Race before him, they had ſmall hopes left them; that any of the ſame line would be much better, being tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor'd afore-hand by the Father, and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reſiding in a French Academy, which if admitted to the Government, in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood would be no other then the cauſe of more blood, more charge, trouble, miſery and ſorrow to the people; very few of our
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119898:45"/> Kings having given the Nation any great cauſe to be over-much enamoured with their Governments, but moſt of the beſt much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, through their Tyrannies and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I profeſs, you have given me fuller ſatisfaction then I could expect; and I believe that you have taken the right meaſure of the Parliaments foot, with the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wherefore they have not onely cut off the Father, but excluded all his Diſcendants; onely in the point of their changing the kingly Government into a Republick as more ſecure and cheaper for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this is a riddle to me; for la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable experience enforms us, that all the oppreſſions and grievances of the people, by all, or moſt of our Kings, and thoſe ſo much upbraided and caft in the face of the late King, I dare affirm amounts not to the fiſth part of the charge and Contributions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on the Natives by the Parliament; if you grant this for truth, as I preſume you cannot gain-ſay it, doubtleſs then the State here in being, have brought the people to a very bad market, ſince 'tis manifeſt, that what by the Monthly Contributions, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous exactions of the Officers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms on all Merchandize, together with the Exciſe on all we eat or drink, with the free
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119898:46"/> quartering of the Souldiers in moſt parts of the Land, are far beyond all the Taxes, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and Subſides which the late King impoſed or intended to lay on the people, which gives them no great cauſe to rejoyce and make merry, either for their ſafety or the cheapneſs of the exchange; Anſwer me to this point, and I ſhall (as the Colonel even now ſaid) give you fair leave to carry away the bucklers, and henceforth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge you for an expert Fencer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thraſo.</speaker>
               <p>God amercy honeſt Doctor, in good faith, thou haſt now given him a bone to pick that will ſtick in his teeth; if he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers this to any purpoſe, he ſhall not onely carry away the Bucklers, but I ſhall willingly give him my ſword into the bargain, and then dam him for me, that will ever fight one ſtroke more in the quarrel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Colonel, you and your party have gotten ſuch a habit of ſwearing, and in ſuch fearful volleys of Oaths, as that had your cauſe been much better then it was, God could not bleſs it or give you any good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs therein: but I beſeech you leave your prophanation, and then have patience a while, for you have very good reaſon to leave fighting, when you are ſo ready to depart with your weapons; but lay your ſword to the ſtake, and then ſee what in the end
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119898:46"/> will become of him; for whatſoever the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor hath objected concerning the preſent impoſitions, (which are confeſt to be very heavie on the poor people) yet when you know all, it would have been much better he had ſaid nothing, ſince I perceive none of you all ever ſounded the late Kings depth and what he intended, or took the leaſt meaſure of his foot; for indeed he was too dark for any of your light to ſee into his deſigns; and to tell you more, he was too cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for any that he employed; though ſome there are which accounted him for little more then an <hi>Iguoramus,</hi> but one of the ſhrewdeſt ones for his reaches to his own ends, of any Prince of his time: True it is, that the Parliament, though they ſuſpected him at the firſt ſitting down, and before, yet knew not a long time what he had in hand, otherwiſe <note place="margin">The Juncto and the Kings Letters taken at <hi>Nasby,</hi> the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly means that the Parliament came to the knowledge of his Intentions.</note> then at random, until the diſcovery of the Juncto, which was the ſtar that guided them to know ſomewhat more of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, then they could clearly diſcern before; and by degrees (as God would have it) more they came both to know and feel, when a long time after his private Letters were taken at <hi>Nasby,</hi> wherein more then
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119898:47"/> enough came to light of his pernicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, or was fitting for a King ſo much courted and beloved of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation) to have attempted for their enſlaving; a deſign (as I have ſaid) though long ſince by ſome of the more intelligent ſort under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, yet till that time never publickly known or viſible; the onely bar to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, was that <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale,</hi> the Prelatical was againſt his Native ſubjects the <hi>Scots,</hi> which brought it ſo about, that the Kings game which was a fair fore-game, became in the end by the <hi>Scots</hi> reſiſtance and managety, to an after and a loſt game; and the truth is, the <hi>Scots</hi> were too ſubtile for all the kings Arbitrary Inſtruments, and underſtood more of his reaches then happily all of us here ſhall ever know. Now Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, as to your Objections concerning the preſent Taxes, Exciſes, Cuſtoms and Free-Quarter, I crave leave for a while to lay them aſide, to which anon I ſhall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly make anſwer; In the mean time, I think fit to preſent you with a Preparative, whereby to ſhew you that all changes and alterations of Government, are and have evermore been accompanied with innumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able difficulties and hardſhips, eſpecially where the ſword begets them; &amp; who knows not but that the ſword is a very chargeable
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119898:47"/> weapon, and ſuch charges are moſt incident to green and new ſprung up Governments, and cannot be avoyded, as in this caſe, and alteration here with us you ſee cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be made good, without a vaſt expence, which neceſſarily ought to be defray'd by the people, for whoſe ſakes and conſervation of the common freedom, their Truſtees the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament thought fit and beſt for their future indemnity to adventure on the change of the Government, and then as the Adage ſpeaks it, They which reap the gains ought to indure the pains; and 'tis moſt true, that although new gotten liberty be a ſweet bait, yet it often fals out that the enjoyment thereof brings with it a great deal of ſufferance, and yet muſt it be born with patience in hope of better times, which may give way to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthering of the ſufferers.</p>
               <p>And ſo to your Objections, which I ſhall anſwer in their ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r; and firſt to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, wherein I ſhall ſhew you the miſtake; ſince it ſeems you look onely at the preſent Impoſitions without minding their cauſes, which as the poſtures of affairs now are, were neceſſitated and inſorc't on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to levie on the Nation; neither do you look back to thoſe times wherein during the late king and his Fathers raign, there was no cauſe or a peece of a reaſon to be given why
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119898:48"/> any Taxes ſhould have been impreſt on the people without their conſents in Parliament; yet for your better learning I ſhall aſſure you, that the very ſame Houſe in <hi>Broad-Street,</hi> wherein the Office of the Exciſe is erected for the States uſe, was 20 Moneths at leaſt before the late Parliaments ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons rented by <hi>Cottington,</hi> and purpoſely for that uſe deſign'd by the King himſelf, though protracted by reaſons of the <hi>Scotch</hi> troubles: As to the Cuſtoms, we all know to what a height they were grown in the late Kings time, to the great regret of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant; but that you may know what far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was much about that time in agitation, there was a private <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide,</hi> That and other Commiſſions in the Signet Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion iſſued out under the Great Seal, wherein twenty eight Lords and Gentlemen were nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and Authorized to raiſe on all the Commodities of the Land, what new Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Impoſitions the Commiſſioners ſhould think ſit, which was the higheſt ſtrain of Arbitrary power, that ever was attempted by any of our Kings.</p>
               <p>As to free-Quarter, it is confeſt to have bin a very g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ievous burthen on the people, not only to pay their Monthly Contributions, but to be for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'t to give the Souldier free-quarter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119898:48"/> whereſoever he march't; But to anſwer you in a word, that grievance hath been a good ſpace ſince taken away, and the Souldier whereſoever he now Quarters, pays both for horſe and mans meat; moreover the States have very much leſſned their Forces, onely retaining ſuch numbers of horſe and foot as may keep in awe ſuch as you Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of the Royal Party, which if not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, it may happily be more hurtful to the Nation, then the not ſecuring of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works againſt the ingrateful <hi>Dutch,</hi> on whom the Malignant party (which are ſtill rotten at the heart) looks upon with a pleaſing eye, in hopes ſo to order their deſigns, as at laſt to bring in the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender, though to their own particular ruine, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſtruction of the poor innocent peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but in farther anſwer to your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, ſuffer me to put you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, what long ſince, and before the late War began, was projected by the late king, when he was in peace and amity with all the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> you ſhall finde it moſt true, that in ſo great a calm of quietneſs divers Regiments of <hi>Germane</hi> horſe were deſigned to be tranſpotted hither to keep all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in awe and under the whip; and in order to that, the Deputy <hi>Straford,</hi> in as calm a time of quietneſs as ever <hi>Ireland</hi> enjoyed, had
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119898:49"/> raiſed there an Army of near ten thouſand Papiſts, which for many Moneths and ſome years together were there both diſciplined, quartered and paid, for the moſt part at the charge of private men, and ſuch as were averſe to his Tyranous courſes; and in addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe grievances on the <hi>Iriſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the imperious Deputy having taken to farm the Cuſtoms of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at an exceſſive under-value, he impoſed on all the Commodities of the Land, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſurpluſage above the Rent he payd to the King. Happily you may here ask the Queſtion, to what end ſuch an Army was there raiſed and quartered on the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and ſo great Taxes imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed on all the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that kingdom? I anſwer, The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty himſelf tells you the reaſon, as you may ſee it in the <note n="*" place="margin">Vide. <hi>The Juncto.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Juncto; You have an Army</hi> (ſays he to the King) <hi>in Ireland to reduce this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> If you put the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion farther, Why to reduce this kingdom being in peace; I ſhall tell you, that Army of foot with the <hi>Germane</hi> horſe were all to be Garriſoned in <hi>England</hi> on free-quarter, to amuſe and keep the people in ſubjection, whilſt the king playd his game for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the <hi>Scots,</hi> &amp; to the Enſlaving of all the three Nations; If again you demand, What
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119898:49"/> the King would have done with ſo vaſt a Treaſure as he intended to raiſe on both Kingdom; the Deputy could have yeelded you a reaſon and preſident for this too, <hi>viz.</hi> to erect Caſtles and Forts in both Kingdoms, <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs his great Structure not far from <hi>Dublin.</hi>
                  </note> Houſes of pleaſure, as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious as Towns, Parks of as large an extent as whole Pariſhes, Masks, Friſcals, Comedies, Tragedies for the Saboth, Banquets, Junkets, and ſuch-like petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancies, wherewith to pleaſe the Queen and the Court Ladies, to gratifie <hi>Madam</hi> Nurſe, her Fidlers and Dancing-Maſters; for reſt aſſured, that the King meant not longer to depend on Parliamentary aſſiſtance for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying of the Court expences, neither to be controld for any irregularity he pleaſed to put in execution; and this (as tenacious as he was) had often dropt from his own mouth; and <hi>Cottington</hi> could openly ſay at his own Table 1638, when a Gentleman of honour told him, <hi>That the beſt way for the King to fill his Coffers, would be by the ayds of Parliament; What needs that</hi> (replies <hi>Cottington?) the King hath other ways in hand to ſupply his wants without Parliaments:</hi> And indeed gentlemen, as it ſeems, you know not what the King had then in agitation; ſome what more I ſhall tell you, that there were certain odd
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119898:50"/> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Dangerous Papers of the Duputies diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</note> Papers of the Deputies, which I finde not were in queſtion at his Arrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for the Parliament had proof enough wherewith to charge him of his intention to alter the Government; but thoſe Papers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate that the deſign was laid, that no man was to ſtir above ten miles from his Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without leave and ſhewing his occaſion, and that no man was to be maſter of his own Train Arms, either for his Domeſtick uſe or the Publick defence, but that every Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars mans Arms were to be depoſited in one Magazin, and in one place, throughout all the Countries of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was any Houſhoulder to be permitted to have the uſe of ſo much as a Pitch-forke without ſpecial licenſe; ſuch a ſtrange change of Soverainty was not only in hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but in the high way of execution, had it not been put by and obſtructed (as already is declared) by the refractory <hi>Scot,</hi> who marr'd all the Kings work, the Deputies, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and <hi>Cottingtons</hi> endevours to have accompliſht the whole deſign; but how Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Juſtice hath diſappointed and diſpoſed of them all, I leave to your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond conſiderations. Now Doctor, if I have not given you a full Anſwer to all your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, would my leiſure permit my longer
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119898:50"/> ſtay, I could give you a little better ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but for the preſent I ſay no more, but examine well the caſe, as the King (before the Wars began) was carrying on his deſigns, and at a time when he had no cauſe at all to attempt as he did, and then take into your more ſerious conſideration the Parliaments caſe and condition which inforc't them for ſafeguard of themſelves and thoſe that truſted them, to leavie men and money, and ſince of neceſſity to Impoſe Contributions on the the people for ſupport of the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and then you will finde a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between one and the others caſe; onely for a cloſe of our Conference, and in farther proof of the premiſes, I beſeech you tell me, wherefore the King (at this laſt Expedition againſt the <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> 1640) Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned <hi>Cottington</hi> Lord-Warden of the Tower, with injunction to ſee that place well Fortified and man'd, which in obedience to his Majeſtie in commands was preſently put Execution, but with ſuch a refuſe of Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <note n="*" place="margin">Billingſly and Suckling.</note> Colonels and Souldiers as could not be match't in all the Kingdom, &amp; then to mount near upon twenty great Guns on the White Tower, with their muſſels turned againſt the City; if you cannot tell the the reaſon, Ile tell it you; That it was
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119898:51"/> to awe the Citizens, out of fear and jealouſie that ſome one or other inſurrection (which the Projectors own guilty conſciences ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to themſelves) might fall out during the Kings abſence in the North, and to mar the work he had then in deſign, before it came to maturity to be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Why then and at the very ſame time, the King ſhould Commiſſion the late Earl of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> a profeſt Papiſt (as <hi>Cottington</hi> was no better) as Lord Preſident of the <hi>Welch-</hi>Marches, commanding the Earl of <hi>Bridge-water</hi> a ſound Proteſtant to deſert that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Letters under his own hand, which on his examination in Parliament wherefor he waved that command, he produced for his juſtification, where the reaſon inſerted was for his ſpecial ſervice (a proper ſervice if you mark it) Now if you demand, What that ſervice might be, I ſhall inſtantly tell you to what purpoſe, as 'twas then ſpoken <hi>publico conſenſu;</hi> neither ever ſince denyed, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſame Earl being Owner of one of the ſtrongeſt <note n="*" place="margin">Ragland.</note> Caſtles in thoſe parts, ſeated amidſt the greateſt neaſt of Papiſts of any one place in the Kingdom, had private Commmiſſion from the King to raiſe 6000 of them for his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119898:51"/> ſervice, and that ſervice was to convoy the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army on their arival, and to joyn with them when the King pleaſed to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport them for maſtering all thoſe Weſtern parts, and to be farther employed as his occaſions ſhould require; for of ſuch kinde of occaſions (though never ſo needleſs, unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and deſtructive, through the whole courſe of his Reign, (as a fate that followed him to the laſt) he would not be unfurni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
               <p>Why then the late Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuſpected Papiſt, was at the very ſame time Commiſſioned for the North parts; you may ſafely aver, there was no very good meaning in theſe exorbitant undertakings; or other reaſon to be given for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant purſuance, but that they all tended to enſlave the three Nations, and to ſubject them all under his Arbitrary Power; If any of you here think otherwiſe, as many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands there are which will not believe it, I ſay no more, but that they want wit, but more wiſdom to make a right judgement, not of things doubtful and hidden, but of matters viſible, and acted on the Theater of the Kingdom: Therefore Gentlemen, be not ſtill blind, neither wilfully ſtupid, but lay your hands to your hearts, and bethink your ſelves wherefore the Parliament be-took
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119898:52"/> themſelves to their defenſive Arms, and the <hi>Scots</hi> on the ſame grounds to ſide with them; can you imagine for any other reaſons, then the conſervation of their joynt intereſt, the freedoms and liberties of both Nations, ſince all the world can witneſs, that they were not onely firſt invaded by the King, but deſigned together with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſaladge; &amp; that on the ſame deſign, he firſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan the quarrel with the late Parliament, and therefore (as 'tis aforetold you) they could not in any reaſon or with ſafety of the people truſt a perfidious Prince any longer with the Government, or admit of any more Kings: but in prevention of worſe evils, which in all probability would happen to the prejudice of the univerſal Nation, to alter the Government, as now you ſee it eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in peace, and in hopes that in ſhort time it may prove much better, ſafer, and leſs burthenſom to the people then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment hath been, which you may be ſure o'nt would have been much worſe, had the Kings deſigns proſpered and taken effect, whether we look back on all the Motions of his Government before the Wars, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on that which had he been Victor, would neceſſarily have befallen the Nation; as to that, God knows, he came very near the accompliſhment: But all of you may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119898:52"/> ſee throughout the purſute, that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God did not, neither could he give a bleſſing to his bloody deſigns, and that a moſt fearful fare hath befallen the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor and his Fathers houſe, together with moſt of his Aſſiſtants in that work of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their bloody and ambitions affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in oppoſition to Gods Law, the Laws of the Land, and that of Natures birth-right; ſo that on a right underſtanding, you which are ſo much devoted and beſotted to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and adore a Tyrant, cut off as well by the hand of Gods juſtice as mans, have rather cauſe with thankfulneſs to adore his infinite Providence in taking him away, &amp; likewiſe to magnifie the Parliament as the inſtrument or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd of God for the preſervation of your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, &amp; the common intereſt of the Nations, much rather then to grutch and repine againſt the preſent ſettlement, rail and ſtorm againſt thoſe Magiſtrates whom God in his great mercy hath ſet over us, under whom, he that will may live quietly and contentedly; as to ſuch as will not, I leave them to their fortune; and ſo Gentlemen, for this time I take my leave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thra.</speaker>
               <p>I vow <hi>Patriotus,</hi> I never till now underſtood ſo much of the Kings intentions; I could wiſh with all my heart, I had known
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119898:53"/> his minde twelve years ſince; Sure I am, he deceiv'd me, and a thouſand more of us, with as fair words and plauſible Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as ever could come from a Chriſtian; but now I perceive your infallible proofs, and many of them as I well remember of his own hand-writing, and of my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that all is not gold that gliſters; and I proteſt on the reputatio of a Souldier, I now begin to have a better opinion of the Parliaments cauſe then hitherto I have had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Good Colonel, I have not the command of your opinion; I leave you to your own election to believe and judge as you ſhall ſee cauſe; onely as you wiſh you had known the Kings minde ſooner, I wiſh he had known himſelf rather; for this <hi>noſce te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum,</hi> the knowledge of our ſelves is the beſt piece of Philoſophy that any of us can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly learn; and as to his fair and plauſible language, whereby to attract to himſelf friends and aſſiſtants, I ſhall tell you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which I believe you took no notice of; for you were deceived in the King who had ſuch a faculty of his own, that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you could not ſay he was ever known to be over-cheap to any whom he found not fit and ſerviceable for that purpoſe, to which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119898:53"/> he would employ him; but on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the wars the caſe was altred; for then it ſtood him upon to be more then ordinarily affable to all you of the Souldiery, ſince he was to make uſe of your ſervice for the accompliſhment of his ends, which with all my heart I have often wiſh't that they had bin better byaſſed; and ſo Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, we muſt have a time to depart, ſinace for theſe five hours or more, we have coſt the ball from one to the other, and yet at laſt how different ſoever in our opinions, I joy in this, that we ſhall depart in love and friendſhip, not doubting but this meeting may make way for another of more mirth and leſs diſtaſte, wiſhing and praying to the God of Peace, that in this univerſal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement of opinions in theſe times, that odium and hatred which ſo unhappily hath been contracted between brethren of one and the ſelf-ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> blood upon the late fatal quarrel, may yet at length be bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that pleaſing Sepulcher of a cordial reconciliation, and that we may all ſubmit, firſt to Gods good will and pleaſure, and next to that Government which by many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible manifeſtations he hath been pleaſed to eſtabliſh, in the room of that which hath been ſo ſanguinary, ſo diſpleaſing to him,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119898:54"/> ſo dolorous &amp; grievous to the poor innocent people, ſo improſperous and detrimental to all parties; and it ſhall be my continual ſute unto him, who is the great King of the World, he that makes and unmakes Kings and States at his onely will and pleaſure, to put a period to our Calamities, which I fear cannot be permitted, as inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with his Juſtice, or appeaſed with bare moralities, but with the realtie of a true and timely repentance, which is the onely ſacrifice and propitiation that he loves, and the ſame for which we ought inceſſantly to pray, it may be given unto us all of this ſinful Nation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prel.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patriotus,</hi> I beſeech you be not ſo haſty to depart before I have made an acknowledgment that you have convinc't me in ſundry particulars, eſpecially by your two laſt Replies, which have given me more light, and better ſatisfaction then ever I received from any man living; And truly Sir, I ſhall ruminate on that which towards the concluſion of your laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply you delivered, and ſo ſhall detain you no longer, but onely to give you hearty thanks with aſſurance that I both love and honout you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patri.</speaker>
               <p>Doctor, in a word more, my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119898:54"/> throughout all our conference have been to make uſe of nothing but plain truth, neither to deliver any thing on bare truſt, or delude you with flams without due proofs; and for concluſion, I wiſh you all to review, and take the particulars following into your ſecond conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, with whom the Parliament had to do, and into what ſtreights, difficulties, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances they were intoy'ld and engaged, which was onely by the continued wiles and practiſes of the late unfortunate King; next into what plunges and neceſſities they were driven for the preſervation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt and ſafety of the Nation, their own perſons and the people by whom they were truſted together, with thoſe neceſſitated and forcible reaſons, which induced them to cut off the late King, as the cauſe of ſo much innocent blood ſpilt, with the excluſion of his Poſterity, &amp; change of the Government. In the next place, take the reaſons of the continuation of the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, for ſecuring thereof, and ſtaving off a ſecond war, which the Malignant Party endevours by bringing in the <hi>Scoth</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender, which ſhould it happen, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability may be more bloody and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable for the people to bear, then the former have been, which by many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119898:55"/> Arguments and demonſtrations in our conference is made manifeſt. The premiſes duly conſidered, cannot be denyed; why then the ſeveral parties in this great diſcrepancy of opinion, ſhould not cloſe in a cordial conjuncture, and unanimous agreement for conſervation of their mutual intereſts, ſeems to me one of the great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the world, but that ſome there are and not a few throughout the Land, which are poſſeſt with a ſpirit of error, and taken with ſuch an Egyptian blindneſs, that they cannot or will not ſee Gods high hand and Providence in this Miraculous change of affairs, neither their own happineſs involved therein, but are led captive through their own wilfulneſs, ſuppoſing to make their condition better by multiplying their own miſeries; ſo fatally beſotted they are with their reſtleſs deſires, by bringing in upon themſelves and the whole Nation, tyranny, ruine, and deſolation: It ſhall therefore be my hearty prayers to Almighty God, to open the eyes of their underſtanding, as I hope Gentlemen, he will in good time, which would be a comfort to all good and honeſt men, to be eye-witneſſes of unity and concord between brethren of one faith, one language, one linage, and withal my heart I wiſh it, of one unanimous ſpirit; then
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119898:55"/> by Gods bleſſing we ſhould be more ſecure at home, and more formidable abroad; and ſo Gentlemen, once more I wiſh you a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, but with this engagement that you ſhall God-willing, ſhortly ſee on what ſandy foundations the King built his deſigns, and on what a rotten building your ſelves fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your hopes, with the groundleſs reaſons which induced you to take part with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidious King, and how you have been all deluded by him under the ſpecious pretence of Law and Loyalty, and that by the ſame way he came at laſt to ruine himſelf and his Poſterity.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:119898:56"/>
            <head>Additionals to the former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for the better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of <hi>Royaliſts</hi> and all others miſtaken in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concerning the late Kings Deſigns, the legality of his Prerogatives, with their deſtructive conſequences, ſhould he have obtained them by the Sword.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter ſo long a time, ſo often Diſputes, and ſo much written of the differences between the late King and Parliament, and after the determination of the Controverſie, and a new Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed, to repeat <hi>de novo</hi> what was acted between both parties known to all of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119898:56"/> underſtanding, I know muſt incnr the ſevere cenſure of the moſt intelligent, ſhould they not look upon the reaſons, and take into their ſecond conſiderations how at this time the preſent poſtures of affairs of State are traduced, cenſured, and cryed down, not onely by the old Royal party, but by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of other malitious diſtempered ſpirirs newly ſtarted up, ſince the diſſolution of the late Parliament, which deny and call into queſtion the verity of moſt paſſages acted on the open Theater of the Nation. This hath induced me to revive and repeat ſome things not vulgarly known, though others, and moſt of that (which I crave leave now to recite) are viſibly known to all the World, and that the enemies to the preſent Government are more now in number then eyer: I held my ſelf bound (as a member of this Commonwealth) to vindicate truth, and to ſatisfie ſuch as ſtill are diffident of the truth of paſſages, as alſo to perſwade others wavering in their belief, to ſtand faſt to their old principles as the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt and moſt ſafe for themſelves in particular, and the common good of all the Nation in general: In purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance whereof having in former the Diſcourſe anſwered ſome of the principal objections of Royaliſts and others againſt the preſent Government, as they are abruptively
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119898:57"/> diſcuſt between the Inter-locutors variouſly and differently affected: We now come to ſhew not only how the King himſelf, but thoſe of his party, have been induced to believe the Soveraignty with thoſe Lawleſs Perogatives claimed by him as inſeparables to the Crown, were of right, and by the Laws of the Land, to be diſpoſed at his onely will and pleaſure as king and the ſupream Governor of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Theſe being the grounds and baſis of the late horrid War, and the reaſons wherefore he pretented to take up Arms to maintain them againſt the Parliament, which, as Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts ſtill conſtantly aver, were invaded by them: 'Tis moſt true, that the Parliament did and by their truſt were bound to oppoſe him in thoſe irregular claims, as inconſiſtent with the nature &amp; conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, contradictory to the Laws, and prejudicial to the Rights and Liberties of the people. Now, foraſmuch as Royaliſts do ſtill conſtantly maintain, that their firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements with the King were undertaken on juſt, loyal, honourable, honeſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious grounds, and that the king ſuffered as an innocent Martyr in his own defence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretexts of his injuſtice and Tyranny, and that themſelves are enforc'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to live under Powers utterly unlawful, uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119898:57"/> and tyrannical; May they be pleaſed to give me leave briefly to ſum up the whole Controverſie (intended for their own good, the quieting of their diſtempered ſpirits, the ſettlement of the univerſal people in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed harmony of peace and unanimity) their onely diſtance and refractory humour to that of the preſent eſtabliſhment being the onely cauſe that the old Rupture cannot be ſodred up and cemented, as it ought to be between brethren of one ſtock &amp; that the States (after their many miraculous Atchievements &amp; Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories over ſo powerful enemies) are inforc'c to the great charge and grievance of the Natives, to keep in pay ſo many Armies for the prevention of ſuch dangerous conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies as are daily hatcht, and ſeen to flow from the fountain of their malitious hearts, whereas their conformity with the reſt of the Natives, in obedience to the preſent powers, would be the ſpeedy remedy and abatement of thoſe heavie and Monethly Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons continued on the people; wherein themſelves would partake in the eaſement; the State and Common-wealth in the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and comfort, that ſo many Proſelytes ſhould be added to their number.</p>
            <p>Now in as much as the nature of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (by way of advice) will neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſome ſhort repetition of the Kings
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119898:58"/> proceedings in the late prodigious War, wherein the grounds of their partaking with him are briefly ſtated; I ſhall intreat the Reader (of what garb or party ſoever) not to conceive that herein I take occaſion to rake over the aſhes of him who is at reſt, but onely for the better manifeſtation of truth (never more oppoſed then at preſent) and to let the univerſal Nation ſee and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand on what ſandy foundations, not onely the King, but the Royaliſts themſelves built the whole fabrick of his deſigns, how, and by whom they were promoted, to his own ruine, his poſterity, and moſt of the Royal party, to the irreparable loſs of three flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Briefly then, that the King at his firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the Crown had it in deſign (as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy legacy left him by his Father King <hi>Iames)</hi> to advance the Regal power to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs, conformable to the <hi>French</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, is a truth ſo perſpicuous, as that divers perſons of honour (then in Court) both perceived it, and feared the ſad iſſues that would follow the Kings ambitious affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; True it is, the deſign a long time was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in the dark and myſtical traverſes of Court and State; but 1638 and 39 the King by his active <note n="*" place="margin">Strafford, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, Cottington.</note> Agents, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared all things in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119898:58"/> readineſs, for the accompliſhment both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the onely rub that then lay in his way of compleating an univerſal invaſſaladge over the three Nations, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Church Government of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſutable to the Epiſcopal Diſcipline of <hi>England,</hi> was the refractory Presbyterian <hi>Scot,</hi> whom he firſt tempted with the bait of a new Liturgy, and whether they ſhould perceive the meaning thereof or not, was (amongſt the firſt Projectors of this Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation here in Court) not much reckoned of; for that in caſe of the <hi>Scots</hi> refuſal, they very well underſtood, the King was reſolved to compel them to ſubmit by force of Arms; but the <hi>Scots</hi> utterly rejecting the Liturgy (as an Innovation and Invaſion on their National Laws and Liberties) the King raiſed his firſt Army againſt them, and then the ſecond (after a Pacification given them;) paſſages ſo commonly known to both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that there needs no farther manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their contrivances. But moſt certain it is, that then the Kings grand deſign began more openly to appear, and that thoſe two Northern Expeditions having exhauſted his Treaſure, with all that he could ſhift for, and the extremity of his want of money ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, produced the firſt and the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119898:59"/> Where we may not omit to ſhew how the King at his firſt entry to the Crown, was after miſled and moſt groſly betray'd, and by perſons (of his own choyce) from the very beginning of his raign to the laſt of his power, who had chiefeſt influence on his Councels, which principally were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and his Court Chaplaines, which more ſtudied his inclinations then Divinty; and then to comply with whatſoever they found moſt agreeable to his natural appetite, which was the uſual ladder wherewith they climbed to preferment; theſe ſycophants well perceiving the bent and promptitude of his ambition to abſolute Soveraingty, had learn'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the faculty of wreſting of Scripture anſwerable to Arbitrary power, and made it their ordinary Pulpit-ſtuff to inſtill into his apprehenſions, that the Subject had no other propriety in any thing he enjoyed but at the Kings good pleaſure: And to theſe there were another ſort of <note n="*" place="margin">Lawyers.</note> Gown-men that could ſtretch Law and Statutes to the tenter of the Kings deſigns; neither were there wanting many about his perſon even from the firſt to the laſt of his Power, that to gain his favour, had learn't the art of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance; ſo that I am confident to affirm
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119898:59"/> (as being often converſant in the Court) that no Prince of his time and of his abilities, was ever ſo nurſt up (what between thoſe Clergy Laquies, and his jugling Judges) in the principles of Tyranny (leaving out thoſe forragn Pedagogues, as well maſculine as femine, always in Court and moſt near his perſon) inſomuch as at laſt he knew not, or would not know the nature and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soveraignty, neither what the nature of thoſe Royal Prerogatives he claimed were, how intruſted and inveſted in him, but took them for no other then his own proper inheritance, to be uſed as his he ſhould think moſt conducible to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of his abſolute power.</p>
            <p>But to return to the late Parliaments firſt ſitting down, and to relate what in the firſt place they fell upon, as of higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to be redreſt, moſt certain it is that they finding the many grievances of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with the various innovations, diſorders, and diſtempers of the State and Church, all concentring in the Kings indigence, they took it into their ſerions conſultations firſt of all to call to an accompt ſuch Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipants of the Kings Councels, as were well known to have been the principal Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for promoting of Arbitrary power,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119898:60"/> and then to apply themſelves to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the Publick diſorders, and rectifying of the obliquities both in the Church and Commonwealth, crept in through the long diſ-uſe of Parliaments. We ſhall onely touch on the moſt eminent paſſages during their firſt fifteen Months ſitting, <hi>viz.</hi> The Attaching and Arraignment of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> the Archbiſhop, the flight of the Lord Keeper <hi>Finch,</hi> Secretary <hi>Windibank, Piercy, Jermine, Suckling,</hi> all of them prime ſticklers for the advance of the Kings deſigns, &amp;c. In the next place, the Kings continued practiſes to corrupt his own Army, and that of the <hi>Scots,</hi> inviting them with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and promiſes of preferment, to march againſt the Parliament, which on any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he was then reſolved to deſtroy; his then ſucceding journey into <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the breaking out of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion during his reſidence there; his aſſault of the Houſe of Commons on his return; his then fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and manning of White-hall with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeers; and when he found that by none of theſe artifices he could break the Parliament, he leaves them and departs to <hi>York,</hi> ſends <hi>Eliot</hi> for the Great Seal, and procures as many as poſſibly he could of both Houſes to falſifie their truſt and adhere to him, ſo to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119898:60"/> divide and deſtract them, and then raiſes an Army, cauſing the Lords there attending him, to atteſt that he raiſed that Army onely for a Guard to his Perſon, and not againſt the Parliament, and immediately ſends out his Commiſſions of Array, and marches through ſeveral Counties to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> where he erected his Standard of War, and after marches to <hi>Edgehill</hi> where he fought with the Parliaments Army, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that before from <hi>Nottingham</hi> he would have perſwaded the Parliament by an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of his own, that he did not ſet up his Standard againſt them; all which and much more of his prodigious Stratagems known to all the World, makes it apparant, that his intent was to deſtroy the Parliament, and conſequently to alter the Government and the Laws as he liſted; and yet there are at preſent a new ſprung-up number of perverſe people amongſt us (beſides the old Royal party) that impudently deny the premiſes, and take occaſion upon this late change and diſſolution of the Parliament, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the Contributions, to aſperſe the preſent Parliament with moſt oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious language. I wiſh they would look back to the cauſe; and how diffident ſoever they are of the kings deſtructive intentions,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119898:61"/> yet may they pleaſe to take a review of his after-actions, and what horrible cruelties and oppreſſions were perpetrated through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moſt parts of the Land, by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, authorized under his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, after he began the War at <hi>Edgehill,</hi> and made <hi>Oxford</hi> his Head quarters; then queſtionleſs they may take the true dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a moſt unfortunate and tyrannical King; neither would it be amiſs for them to take it into their remembrance, what the Parliament in ſo perplext times were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to put in execution, as well for their own ſafeties as the preſervation of the Laws and Liberties of the people.</p>
            <p>Thus far in brief we have made a recital of the principal tranſactions before that fatal battel at <hi>Edgehil,</hi> whence all Royaliſts and others diffident of the Kings deſtructive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, may evidently ſee unto what plunges the Parliament was put unto upon the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, in relief of their poor diſtreſſed brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that affair by the King himſelf bring wholy recommended to the Parliaments diſpoſement, &amp; 400000l. in Subſidies aſſented by himſelf to be levied to that onely uſe, and the Earl of <hi>Leyceſter</hi> by his own approbation deſign'd for that imployment, whom he ſo long protracted,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119898:61"/> that the term of his Commiſſion was near expired before he went over; and as to his proclaiming them Rebels, to which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament often preſt him, he would not in a long time ſuffer his Proclamations to come forth; and at laſt, permitted no more then 40 Copies to be printed; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe his impediments, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with their beſt Expedition ſent over divers Regiments of foot, ſome horſe and cloathes by the way of <hi>Minyard</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi> The premiſes conſidered by any indifferent man, with what honour then or juſtice could the king countermand thoſe Forces, and ſeize the cloathes, horſes and money ſent to the relief of the poor diſtreſſed <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants againſt his own Act and Aſſent? and by what law or colour of Reaſon could he in honor grant the remainder of the third part of that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie to his Lieutenant-General of South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>Wales,</hi> for raiſing of an Army there againſt the Parliament, diverting the uſe thereof for the relief of <hi>Ireland?</hi> What anſwer can be made to this, other then that which with impudence of the higheſt ſtrain is commonly alledged by Royaliſts? <hi>viz.</hi> That the king ſtood bound both in honour and reaſon of State to ſupport the Rebellious
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119898:62"/> 
               <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in what poſſibly he could, ſo to leſſen the Parliaments power by what means ſoever for advance of his own: If this be the reaſon, ſurely then 'tis evident, that he not onely favoured the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but authorized their Inſurrection, and that his intent was to incumber and cut out as much work for the Parliament as poſſibly he could invent, and in that courſe to protract the War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to purſue it in <hi>England,</hi> as 'tis moſt manifeſt he did during full ſix years together; neither would he be induced by the Parliaments many and moſt humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, really to apply himſelf to a ſafe and well-grounded Peace for the Nation, though ſtill pretending how willing he was to embrace it, when as by the ſequel he intended to have it no other then as ſuted to his own will and pleaſure; and yet all of the Royal party as conſtantly defends him, as himſelf obſtinately perſiſted (ſo long as his power laſted) to embrew all the three Nations with blood, fire, and devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to his laſt <note n="*" place="margin">Vide, <hi>The Kings Speech on the Scaffold.</hi>
               </note> hour ſtood ſtiffly in the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that the abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Militia</hi> was his; and that the Parliament on that only ground, firſt began the War, and not he, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119898:62"/> to his own acknowledgement in the Ile of <hi>Wight</hi> and elſwhere, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had been the cauſe of all the innocent blood ſpilt throughout the Land; I wiſh he were not guilty of that in <hi>Ireland:</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions being ſo pregnant, as that thouſands of honeſt and knowing men cannot be otherwiſe perſwaded; ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, he was moſt notoriouſly guilty of all the blood ſpilt in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now come to the kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives as the baſis on which all Royaliſts ground the lawfulneſs of their partaking with him in the late War, as bound by Oath, their Allegiance, and in conſcience to ſupport his Soveraign Rights; We ſhall for their better ſatisfaction, preſent them in a Catalogue, and anſwer them in their order; foraſmuch as they ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly maintain them to be the kings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably united to the Crown; and that full ſore againſt his will, he was inforc't to uphold them as invaded by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; ſince then that (as Royaliſts aver) the King onely fought to uphold his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance and themſelves with him; let us briefly examine by what Law and right
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119898:63"/> he claimed them, together with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrctive conſequences, ſhould he have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them by the ſword, and whether then he had not carved out his own work to the enſlaving of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:119898:63"/>
            <head>Of the Prerogatives Royall, which the late King claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as inſeparables of the Crown.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. OF the Royal Power, what it is.</item>
               <item>2. His ſole and abſolute power over the <hi>Militia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. His Negative voyce in all Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
               <item>4. His power to Array the people at will and pleaſure.</item>
               <item>5. His Prerogative to call and diſſolve Parliaments at pleaſure.</item>
               <item>6. His Prerogative to pardon Murderers and Fellons.</item>
               <item>7. His Prerogative to diſpoſe of Wards, Mad-men and Lunaticks, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>8. Laſtly, that Tyrannous aſſertion of his own and his Father King <hi>Iames, viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:119898:64"/> That they were not bound to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their actions to any but to God alone.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe Prerogatives claimed by the late King, as the Royaliſts ſay, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by the Parliament, and the grounds of the late deſtructive Wars; happily after-Ages as well as the preſent, may be inquiſitive to know whether they were ſo legally in the Kings abſolute power, that he ſtood bound to uphold them by the ſword to the ruine of the Kingdom? and whether the Parliament (by their truſt) ſtood not more obliged to withſtand them as encroachments on the common freedoms and liberties of the people? We ſhall therefore (for the general ſatisfaction) briefly ſhew the extent of them all, as they are either defined by our ancient Lawyers, or confined and limited by our common Laws and Statutes.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Royal power, what it is.</head>
               <p>FIrſt then, that this Royal power of our Kings, hath never been any other then a limited and intruſted power to govern by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119898:64"/> Law, to which their Coronation Oathes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them, which may very well ſatisfie any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man, and ſave us the labour farther to diſpute this point. But we ſhall make it more plain, that the higheſt of this Royal power was never more by the Law of the Land (throughout all Ages) then in the executive power, <hi>Ius ſuum cuique tribuere,</hi> to give to every ſubject his right; neither can the King otherwiſe diſpence this right or Law to the people, but in and by his Courts of Judicature, <hi>non per ſe tantum,</hi> not by himſelf out of the law of his own breaſt; for that's plain Tyranny; <hi>Stat pro ratione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas; &amp; quod principi placuit, legis habet vigorem</hi> (which are the common principles of all Tyrants) that, That ſhall be the Law which the king wills, which is more then the Grand Signior claims or exerciſeth; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this Royal power (whatſoever of late times by flattering Lawyers hath been expoſed to deceive the people) enable the king to do that which the Law forbids. What kings as Tyrants will do, makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the matter in queſtion, but what they ought to do, and what by the Law, their Oath, and duty of their Office, they are bound to do, is the true ſtate of this Queſtion: Neither were any of our kings
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119898:65"/> ever ſo abſolute in power and Supremacy, but that by the fundamental Laws of this Land, they had their Superiours, and thoſe which were above them, as one of the moſt eminent and ancient of our <note n="*" place="margin">Bracton.</note> Lawyers affirms, (often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited during the late Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie) <hi>viz. Rex habet ſuperiorem, ſcilicet legem, per quam factus eſt Rex; alterum, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet curiam, comites, &amp; Barones;</hi> which is, The king hath a ſuperiour, to wit, the Law by which he is made king, another (though very much ſcorned by the late king) <hi>viz.</hi> The Court of Parliament compoſed of the Earls, Barons and ſelected Gentry of the Land; for this Court hath in it the Legiſlative power or the Authority of making Laws; and who knows not the old principle, <hi>Quod efficit tale, eſt magis tale;</hi> that which makes the thing, is greater then the thing made? And another of our eminent and learned Lawyers, <hi>Fortiſcue</hi> Chancellour to <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth. <hi>fol.</hi> 40. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. poſitively delivers it as a fundamental Law, that the kings power is no other then that which the Law gives him, and that cannot be farther extended or made greater without the aſſent of the whole Realm; for ſhould it be otherwiſe, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that the king might then ſell, or diſpoſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119898:65"/> of the kingdom to whom he pleaſeth, which by the Law he cannot do; neither (by the ancient Laws of the Land) can the king ſell, or alienate the <hi>Regalia</hi> and Jewels of the Crown (though the late king took the liberty to ſell them for Arms againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) neither can the King by his own ſole power, diſpoſe of the Cities, Towns, Forts, and Caſtles of the Kingdom, as the <hi>Scotch</hi> Lords 1639 told him in down-right terms on his fortifying of the Caſtles of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> and <hi>Dunbarton;</hi> and the reaſons they gave, were valid both in Law and reaſon; for that thoſe Forts and Caſtles were built for defence, ſecurity and ſafety of the people againſt Invadors, and not for their offence to be man'd and fortified at the Kings pleaſure againſt themſelves; And the reaſon of this Law is rendred by a moſt learned and expert <note n="*" place="margin">Novil. 85. princi. cap. 18.</note> Juriſt, viz. <hi>Quod Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus ſit nudus diſpenſator &amp; defenſor Iurium Regni, conſtat ex eo quod non poſsit alienare Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium, oppida, urbes, regioneſve, vel res ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorum, bonave Regni, quia Rex Regni non proprietarius:</hi> Which is, that a King or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is no more then a bare diſpenſor of the Laws of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Kingdom; and the reaſon is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, for that he cannot ſell or alenate the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119898:66"/> Kingdom, or the Cities, Towns and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces thereof, neither the Subjects goods, or goods of the Kingdom, becauſe the King is onely the Director, not the Owner and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priator of the kingdom: But Royaliſts and ſome jugling <note n="*" place="margin">Judge <hi>Ienkins.</hi>
                  </note> Lawyers and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Divines, have both taught and written the contrary, and made the late king believe that his power was abſolute and without bounds, which is fearful to imagine, and ſhameful in thoſe which continue to poſſeſs the people with ſuch damnable untruths, as lamentable it is to ſee the generality of the Nation to ſtand ſtill unſhaken in their belief that the kings rights were invaded, and himſelf inforc'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make war for his own; the contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that his power ſtood bounded and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by the Laws of the Land, hath been ſo often alledged and preſt upon him by the Parliament, in their Anſwers and Expreſſes, that the re inforcing of more Arguments on a ſubject ſo much overworn would be nauſeous to all ingenious Readers.</p>
               <p>To period this particular, as 'tis the gound-work of all the kings other Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative claims, I ſhall onely put all Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts in remembrance of that which the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> aver'd to the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119898:66"/> king 1640. <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vide, <hi>The Iuncto.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>looſe and abſolved from all the reines of Government;</hi> whether this aſſertion (amongſt other of the Deputies) tended not to place the kings power above the known Laws of the Land, I appeal to the judgement of any rational man; for as a late, a worthy
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Pim,</hi> in his Speech to the Lords.</note> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Parliament obſerved at the Earls tryal, that the Laws were the boundaries and meaſures betwixt the Kings Prerogative, and the peoples Liberty: But whether the king throughout the whole courſe of the late deſtructive War, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome years before, was not a prompt diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Deputies doctrine, I leave to Royaliſts to make their own judgement. And whether that which after befell the king and his Fathers houſe, was not rather of the juſtice of heaven then of men, I leave to the judgement of all the world. Sure we are, the beſt Juriſts maintain, <hi>Si Rex hoſtili animo arma contra populum geſſerit, amittet Regnum;</hi> which is, that if a King with an hoſtile intent ſhall raiſe Arms againſt his people, he loſeth or forfeits his kingdom: Now, that the late king aſſumed to himſelf ſuch a Royal power as to raiſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119898:67"/> Arms againſt the great Councel of the Land, I ſuppoſe no man in his right wits can deny Its moſt true, a moderate Royal power to rule by the Laws, is doubtleſs of Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; but a Tyrannical power to cut their throats, I am ſure is of no Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a Dominion fitter for beaſts then men; yet this is that power which Royaliſts would have faſtned on the king; and too many there are which conſtantly believe that the more injury was done him, that he had it not, as by the Laws of the Land they erroneouſly conceive he ought to have had.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> how the Kings.</head>
               <p>BRiefly now to the <hi>Militia,</hi> and what kinde of power our kings by the Laws of <hi>England</hi> have had therein: It hath been often told the late king (all along the late Controverſie) that the power of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> was in him no other then fiduciary, and not at his abſolute diſpoſe, or that at his own will and pleaſure he might pervert
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119898:67"/> the Arms and ſtrength of the kingdom from their proper uſe, and againſt the intent of the Law (as 'its viſibly known he did even to the higheſt breach of truſt wherein a king could be intruſted:) Now for proof, that this power was onely fiduciary, and by Statute Law firſt confer'd on <note n="*" place="margin">Anno 7. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. apud Weſtminſter.</note> 
                  <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. in truſt, and not his by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, is moſt apparent, by the Expreſs words of the Statute it ſelf, which (as they are commonly inſerted) were onely for the the defence of the Land and ſafety of the people, <hi>(ſalus populi)</hi> being that grand Law and end of all Laws; now ſuch as are verſt in our Hiſtorie, know that this Prince was one of the moſt magnanimous kings that ever ſwayd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Scepter; and therefore it cannot be imaginable that he would clip his own power, and ſo great a right belonging to him by the Common Law, in accepting a leſs by Statute Law, to his own loſs of power, or that ever he would have aſſented thereunto, by an after Act of his own, as follows in <hi>haec verba,</hi> viz. <hi>Whereas on ſundry complaints made to us by the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament, that divers of the ſtanding Bands have been removed and taken out of their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119898:68"/> reſpective Counties by vertue of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions, and ſent to us out of their Shires, into</hi> Scotland, Gaſcoyn <hi>and</hi> Gwoyn, <hi>and other parts beyond the Seas contrary to the Laws of the Land, &amp;c. Our Soveraign Lord willeth that it ſhall be done ſo no more.</hi> Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this we finde, <hi>Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. viz. <hi>The King willeth that no man henceforth be charged to arm otherwiſe then he was wont in time of our Progenitors, the Kings of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and that no man be compell'd to go out of his Shire, but where neceſsity requireth, and the ſudden coming in of ſtrange Enemies into the Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the ſame kings time, there being a peace concluded between him and the <hi>French</hi> king, wherein the Duke of <hi>Britain</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, whom the <hi>French</hi> king ſhortly thereupon invaded, whereof complaint was made to king <hi>Edward,</hi> he inſtantly ſummons a Parliament, and there moves the Lords and Commons, both for their advice and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, whereupon it was concluded, that the king ſhould be expeditiouſly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd in ayd of the <hi>Britton;</hi> but the Act was made with ſuch proviſoes and reſtrictions, as Royalliſts happily, and others of late years would have deemed them too diſhonourable and unbefitting the late kings acceptance;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119898:68"/> howſoever this Act ſhews that the ordering of the <hi>Militia</hi> (of thoſe times) was not ſolely left to the kings diſpoſure; but that which is of more note, was, that both the Treaſure then granted, was committed to certain perſons in truſt to be iſſued to the onely uſe for which it was given; as alſo that no Treaty or any new peace or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould be made without the conſent and privity of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; By theſe inſtances all Royaliſts may make a clear judgement, that the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of thoſe times, and the power of the Arms of the Kingdom were never ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely conferr'd on our kings, as that their power therein extended to ſuch a latitude as they might uſe them as they pleaſed, and to turn that power (provided for the onely defence of the people) againſt themſelves; and therefore whereſover we finde the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> by other Statutes conferr'd, and yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the diſpoſal of our kings, without any particular mention of the word (truſt) which is neceſſarily imply'd, or expreſt in moſt of the Statutes or their preambles, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note that theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> for the defence of the Realm, or common profit are afore inſerted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither in the Stat. them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or in their preamb.</note> In theſe wotds, <hi>For the honour of God, the Church, common profit of the Realm, or defence of our people;</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:119898:69"/> No man in common reaſon can conceive the <hi>Militia</hi> to be ſuch an inſeparable flower of the Crown, as if it had been brought into the world with the King, and chain'd unto him as his birth-right, but onely as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive power recommended unto him by the people in their Repreſentatives, as the moſt eminent and illuſtrious perſon to be intruſted with ſuch choyce weapons, in truſt and confidence that he will uſe them no otherwiſe then to the end for which-they were concredited unto him as the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of the people, and for their onely ſafety and defence which truſted him in honour of his perſon and place; Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Statutes there are (though ſome of them repealed) which prove the <hi>Militia</hi> is onely fiduciary, and not abſolutely inherent to the Crowns of our Kings.</p>
               <p>Now for our concluſion of this ſenceleſs &amp; illegal Prerogative (as to the abſolute power thereof) let us in a word take notice of the deſtructive conſequence; admitting this power ſhould be left to the Kings abſolute diſpoſure, it then follows that he may take all that the Subject hath (for he that hath the power of the ſword, on the ſame ground may command the purſe,) which the late King not onely intended but practiſed; witneſs the many great ſums of money, plate, jewels and other
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119898:69"/> moveables whatſoever taken either by his command or permiſſion in the late Wars; the inſtances whereof would amount to a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn; and as to his intentions, without injury to his memory, we may take notice of his own expreſſions, in his Letters to the Queen; <hi>viz. That though he wanted money, yet good ſwords and Piſtols would fetch it in; Ex un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Leonis;</hi> We may judge of the Lyons ſtrength by his paw, and of the kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, had he lighted on the fortune to have maſtered the Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the Kings Negative Voyce in Parliament.</head>
               <p>WE now come to that ſo much aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and inſeparable Flower of the Crown (as the king and Royaliſts would have it believed,) <hi>viz.</hi> his Negative voyce in Parliament; a claim ſo abſurd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law and Reaſon, that wiſe men may laugh at it, and fools diſcern the diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive conſequence thereof; for at one blaſt or breath of the kings, it utterly fruſtrates the very Eſſence and Being of all Parliaments,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119898:70"/> and obſtructs all their Conſultations; and whatſoever they ſhall never ſo well adviſe and agree upon as a neceſſary Law, ſhall be made of no effect with this one ſingle word of the kings <hi>(Negatur)</hi> which is point blank againſt his Corronation Oath, where he ſwears or ought to ſwear to Govern both by the old Laws, <hi>&amp; per iſtas bonas leges quas vulgus eligerit,</hi> (though it pleaſed the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop to emaſculate that moſt eſſential part of the Oath, ſo to leave the king at liberty) and by ſuch good Laws as the Parliament ſhall chuſe, ſo that the Legiſlative power hath always reſided in that Soveraign Court to make and unmake Laws according to the viciſſitude of times and change of mens manners, and not at the kings choyce, who hath only the diſtributive power, when Laws are made to ſee them duly executed; and the Law of the Land alſo limits that power; for the king, (as before 'tis noted) cannot exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Laws at his own pleaſure, but in and by his Courts of Juſtice. But ſtrange it is, what a ridiculous conſtruction Royaliſts have made of the verb <hi>eligerit,</hi> to be meant in the preterperſect Tenſe and not of the future, to make any new Laws (though never ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary) but that the people muſt ſtand to their old Laws (though ſome of them
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119898:70"/> never ſo fit to be abrogated) unleſs the king pleaſe to give way to the eſtabliſhing of new, or repealing of the old, which is a moſt irrationall and deſtructive aſſertion: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we omit to ſhew what Royaliſts farther aver, that ſuch is the neceſſity and force of the Kings aſſent, that be the Law never ſo uſeful and beneficial for the people to be eſtabliſhed, yet without the Kings <hi>(fiat)</hi> it can never have the force and ſtamp of a Law; which is the ſame as when the King choſen Generaliſſimo, and truſted with the conduct of the Kingdoms Armies, will turn the mouth of the Canon from the Enemy on his own Souldiers, and deny them to provide for their own ſafeties: ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities have the late and preſent Licenciates of this time ran into, as if men had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch't to betray their own freedoms; It is not denyed, but that the Kings aſſent to a Law (thought fit by the Parliament to be Enacted) is very neceſſary; yet it follows not that it muſt be of neceſſity; for if the King out of a perverſe humour will not (after ſome time of conſideration) aſſent to ſuch a Law, which if not ratified by his <hi>(fiat)</hi> tends to the inevitable deſtruction of the Common-wealth, ſhall the publick ſafety be neglected for the humoring of one mans
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119898:71"/> obſtinate will? and in ſuch a caſe ought not the States Aſſembled in Parliament provide againſt a common miſchief, Enact and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain for the publick indemnity as former Preſidents in ſuch caſes may direct them, and when no other remedy can be had? The Lords in the time of king <hi>Richard</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, would not be ſo anſwered, when they ſent him word that if he would not come to the Parliament (according to his promiſe) and joyn his helping hand to theirs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the publick grievances, they would chuſe ſuch a King that ſhould.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Array of the People.</head>
               <p>WE now come to the principal and practical part of the kings power over the <hi>Militia;</hi> for the Array of the people is the grand piece of that uſurpatious claim; <hi>viz.</hi> That at his own will and pleaſure he may ſend forth his Commiſſions to Array the people againſt themſelves; and this power (under colour of Law, and of right belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him) the univerſal Nation knows he forbore not to put in execution againſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119898:71"/> their Repreſentative, ſummoned by his own Writs, a preſident without preſident, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the legality known either in our Hiſtories or Law-books, otherwiſe then by conſent of Parliament, and in caſes of immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment danger for oppoſing of an invading Enemy; but for a king truſted with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his people, in calms of peaceable times, and on no neceſſity, to put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a reaſonleſs and unlimited power, as one of his Royal Prerogatives, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it by the ſword, was beſides the breach of his Royal truſt; ſuch a daring action, as none but a Tyrant in folio would have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted. 'Tis true, that heretofore, during that long continued feud between the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> divers Gentlemen of the North parts and others on the <hi>Welch</hi>-Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the kings Tenants, were by their Tenures bound to riſe, watch and wind <note n="*" place="margin">Cornage Tenure.</note> horns, on all incurſions of the <hi>Scots;</hi> and of theſe kind of Tenures, <hi>Littleton</hi> treats in his chapter of petty Serjeanty; but I ſuppoſe none ſo very cowards (though not bound by their Tenures) but would take up Arms in the common defence, and contribute their beſt aſſiſtance for the expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an invading Enemy, though in this
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119898:72"/> very caſe (by the Law of the Land.) 'Tis very dangerous for him, that ſhall raiſe Forces without ſpecial Commiſſion from the King and Parliament; and
<note n="*" place="margin">The Lords <hi>Cromwels</hi> Caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Cromwel</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eigth's Reign, (though at that time Lord Preſident of the North) dyed for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe then this, that he raiſed an Army both for the ſuppreſſion of an inſurrection, and expulſion of the <hi>Scots;</hi> ſo nice and provident our Anceſtors have ever been of levying Armies in the bowels of the Land on any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; But for the king firſt to raiſe an Army at <hi>York,</hi> aſſuring the Parliament that it was to no other end then for a Guard to his Perſon, and therewith to cauſe ſo many half-witted Lords (then attending him) to atteſt that for truth, which was falſe, as it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeared by his immediate marching to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> where he ſet up his Standard of War, as a ſummons of the people to his aſſiſtance againſt the Parliament, when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was both the firſt Aſſaulter and Invader: and yet at that very inſtant of time, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſure the Parliament, that he raiſed not his Standard againſt them: and at the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of time to ſend out his Commiſſions
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119898:72"/> of Array, was doubtleſs ſuch a breach of Truſt, and a Treachery of ſo deep a die, as that in all our Hiſtories we finde it not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd amongſt all our kings, but onely in that Tyrant of Tyrants king <hi>Iohn,</hi> who indeed invaded the Land, and ruined the Caſtles, and Houſes of the Barons &amp; Gentry that oppoſed his Tyrany, and came not to his aſſiſtance at a call; and in this kinde of Tyranny, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gainſaid, the late king came not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, if not exceeding that irregular king, as 'twas evident by this inſtance, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the ſending forth of his Commiſſions of Array, on the heels of thoſe, iſſued out his Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer &amp; Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner,</hi> to hang all thoſe which adhered to the Parliament. But in a little more to the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legality of the kings Commiſſions of Array, both before and after the ſetting up of his Standard; ſurely thoſe Lawyers that waited on him firſt at <hi>York,</hi> and after at <hi>Oxford,</hi> were doubtleſs thoſe which miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him, and with ſuch artifices and pains drew up his Anſwer to the Parliaments Declaration of the firſt of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1642, againſt the legality of the Commiſſions of Array. He that will take the pains to examine that Declaration compared with the kings Anſwer, may ſoon perceive that the Contrivers and Penners
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119898:73"/> thereof were not ſo honeſt as they ſhould have bin, neither as it ſeems ſo wel read in the Laws, or ſo expert workmen, as to avouch the Statute of the 4. &amp; 5. of <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4. 150 times over in that Anſwer, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their endeavors, to entruſt the King with a legal power to ſend forth his Commiſſions for arraying of the people at his own will and pleaſure without conſent of Parliament; yet thoſe fine <hi>Iohns</hi> for the king, have not, neither could they produce any ſcrap of Law or piece of Statute that enables the king to Array the people againſt themſelves, to engage <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> and to ſet ſo many as came into his aſſiſtance together by the ears with thoſe which adhered to the Parliament, and at a time when there was not the leaſt fear or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of an invading Enemy, more then of thoſe which the Parliament feared ſhould be ſent him out of <hi>France, Lorrain,</hi> and <hi>Denmark;</hi> but to what other ends then to ruine the Parliament, let any impartial Royaliſt make his own judgement; 'tis true, that in caſe of Forraign invaſions the king by Law hath been evermore truſted as Generaliſſimo to command the Force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Kingdom, for defence and ſafety of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to no other end; and ſo was the Law
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119898:73"/> expounded in Parliament, the thirteenth of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but never ſo wreſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by any of our Lawyers, as by thoſe that waited on the King, would have enforc't thereby to impower him at pleaſure, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſtrength of the Kingdom againſt it ſelf; and ſurely it appears to me and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more, that forty Judges, Serjeants, and Lawyers, then in both Houſes of Parliament, ſhould better underſtand and know more of the Law, in the caſe of Commiſſions of Array, then thoſe eight or ten
<note n="*" place="margin">Littleton, Banks, Lane, Heath, <hi>the Atturney</hi> Herbert, Palmer, &amp;c.</note> ſycophant fellows that followed, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the King in ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular motions, onely in hopes of preferment, and to form him into ſuch a poſture of abſolute power, that when he pleaſed he might deſtroy himſelf and the Kingdom, as that to our grief we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they had taught him, and put him in the high-way of the accompliſhment. I remember a pertinent paſſage related in our Hiſtories, how that the Earls of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> and <hi>Leyceſter</hi> being peremptorily ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to attend <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt into <hi>France,</hi> the Earls in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> told him, that by the Laws of the Land they were not bound to wait on him out of the Land at his pleaſure, but onely within the Realm and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119898:74"/> for the defence thereof, and that onely on Invaſions of Forraign Enemies; which agrees with that before recited of his taking the Train-men out of their reſpective Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by his Commiſſions, to ſerve him in <hi>Gaſcoyn, Gwyn,</hi> and other places beyond the Seas, contrary to the Laws of the Land, which grievance the King then redreſt; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could I ever yet finde any one expreſs Law or Statute that enables any of our Kings by their ſole power without conſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to Array the people, but onely in the caſe of Forraign Invaſions, and coming in of ſtrange Enemies; howſoever the Penners of the Kings Anſwer to the Parliaments Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, have laboured (though to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) to prove it otherwiſe; however 'tis worth the obſervation, what fruitleſs pains they have taken in their frequent reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of the Statutes of the 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, the 13. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1. <hi>Ed:</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 25. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 9. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. the 4. &amp; 5. of <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Iacobi,</hi> with divers others, all of them principally tending to the Aſſize of Arming the Subject <hi>ſecundum facultates,</hi> according to his ability; thoſe Aſſizes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been almoſt in every Raign altered, and the Statutes according to the viciſſitudes of times, change of Arms, and invention of Guns, for the moſt part of them repealed,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119898:74"/> and new Statutes made in their rooms with power of Commiſſions to be iſſued as the exigency of affairs ſhould require on In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions from abroad, home defence on In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, &amp;c. All which ſo often and ſo much preſt in the Kings Anſwer made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the matter in queſtion, between him and the Parliament 1642. The point in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, was not then concerning the old Commiſſions of aſſizing Armes, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of Lieutenancies in every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but the reaſons of the Parliaments De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and the exceptions they took, were againſt that exorbitant power the King aſſumed to himſelf under pretext of Law, to Array the people one againſt the other, and againſt their Repreſentative, as that ſure enough he failed not to put in practiſe, howſoever diſguiſed under an elaborate and ridiculous Anſwer, when (as we have noted before) there is not one Statute or ſcrap of Law to be found in all our Law-books, that legally enables the King to raiſe war againſt a Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and raiſe combuſton in the bowels of the Kingdom; which I truſt may ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all Royaliſts, that the Parliament had then good cauſe to complain, when in times of Peace he made them times of war and deſolation, by ſending out thoſe his
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119898:75"/> illegal and deſtructive Commiſſions, which whether they were ſo or not, doubtleſs the Parliament was better able to judge and determine then the King or his Minions then attending his Perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the Kings Prerogative to call and diſſolve Parliaments at his own will and pleaſure.</head>
               <p>AS to the Kings power to call and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Parliaments at his will &amp; pleaſure, to ſummon a Parliament with one breath, and blow it away with another blaſt of his mouth (as 'tis ſtill frequently maintained by Royaliſts and others newly ſtarted up, that by Law and preſidents he was enabled to do) is an aſſertion ſo irrational, as that I wonder not ſo much at their ignorance, as their audacious language; ſince 'tis the known Law of the Land, and by two Statutes of near 400 years ſtanding, ordained, That Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſhall be call'd once every year, and oftner as the emergency of affairs may give occaſion; why then it ſhould reſt in the kings onely power to call them, and that his aſſent to a Triennial Parliament ſhould be ſuch a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119898:75"/> boon beſtowed on the people, ſurely may encreaſe the wonder, ſince by our old Laws and the uſuages of former times, they ought not to be diſſolved, until all grievances be heard and redreſt; otherwiſe to what end or uſe were Parliaments Inſtituted? which as one calls them, are the Beaſoms that ſweep clean all the naſty corners of the Common-Wealth. But obſerve the ſad conſequences of this abſurdity; for ſuppoſe the King would not call any Parliament in ten or twelve years together till his neceſsities inforc't him, how then ſhould the publick grievances be redreſt, and by whom ſhall the diſorders and obliquities of the Church and Commonwealth be rectified? Royaliſts An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by the king alone, or his Councel of State, as the ſuprem Magiſtrate within his own Dominions; A ſtrange task ſurely for one man to undergo, and more then that active Magiſtrate <hi>Moſes</hi> was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, as we may ſee by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Iethro's</hi> Counſel, who adviſed to take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his aſsiſtance, the Princes and beſt of the people to ayd him in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and all that with the leaſt in a populous Nation. Well then, let it be conſidered how many grievous enormities and diſorders (during that interval of ten years diſcontinuance at
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119898:76"/> leaſt of Parliaments) were crept into the Church and State (meerly through their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe) we have ſorry cauſe to remember, when through the pangs of the kings neceſsities, the ill managery of the publick affairs, the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of the Court, the corruption of all Courts of Juſtice &amp; the Judicature, with the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs of a diſſolute Clergy, inforc't him at laſt to cal the late Parliament; yet how ſoon he endevoured by his many wiles &amp; practiſes to annihilate it, nay, by all poſſible means he could invent, hindred their endeavors, in reducing the Church and Common-wealth into order, never ceaſing to interrupt their conſultations, purpoſly to diſorder and thruſt all into a Chaos of confuſion, inſomuch as to this day, the Parliament have had their hands full to finde out the means how to reduce and ſettle things in that order as at firſt they might have been, had not the publick affairs been obſtructed, and all reformation hindred by his onely means, ſo to render them as odious to the future, and as contemptible to the people, as heretofore they were bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and deſired of them; notwithſtanding that at their firſt ſitting down he promiſed to contribute his own Authority to theirs, and to leave the re-ordering of all things amiſs to their onely managery, an overture ſo acceptable unto them, as that in retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119898:76"/> thereof, how willing and intentively bent they were (in the midſt and heat of their diſtractions) to make him rich and glorious; and how indulgently ready to cover his faults in the recovery of his honour at home, and his reputation abroad, none unleſs blinde men, or beſotted, but may remember: But the truth was, he could not brook any Rival with himſelf in the Government, purſuing to the laſt his deſign of abſoluteneſs ſo long, that in the end the Parliament was inforc't not to retain any longer ſuch a Rival as a King amongſt them, but rather choſe to eſtate the people in the ſame peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as we ſee it now eſtabliſhed, then to imagine themſelves able to better it by retaining of Kingſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the Kings Prerogative in granting of Pardons to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers and Fellons.</head>
               <p>WE now come to that Prerogative, or rather lawleſs uſuage of our Kings in granting their Charters of pardon to Murtherers and Fellons condemn'd by the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119898:77"/> Laws of the Land. 'Tis confeſt, that it hath been practiſed by all or moſt of our Kings, though as it may be ſuppoſed, rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively then by vertue of any Law extant; but by what warrant in Juſtice they have aſſumed ſuch a Soveraign power to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, will be the queſtion; for by Gods Law, 'tis abſolutely forbidden; <hi>Yee ſhall take no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the life of a murtherer which is guilty of death, but he ſhall be ſurely put to death.</hi> Numb. 35. 31. and verſ. 33. <hi>Ye ſhall not pollute the Land wherein ye dwell, for blood defileth the land; and the land cannot be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the blood that is ſhed therein, but by the blood of him that ſhed it.</hi> Thus much briefly may ſuffice as to Gods Law; Now as to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> the King cannot pardon a Murtherer or Fellon condemn'd by the Laws of the Land, without a plain breach of thoſe Laws and his Coronation Oath; for <hi>Anno</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, it was by Act of Parliament ordain'd, that Charters of pardon ſhould not be granted but onely where the King may do it by his Oath. And further amongſt this Kings often breaches of the Laws, this very particular of his frequent granting of pardons to Murtherers was complained of in open Parliament; and the King by three ſeveral <note n="*" place="margin">4. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. I dem 16.</note> Acts was reſtrained in thoſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119898:77"/> caſes; but how faulty both the late Kings were in pardoning both Murtherers &amp; Fellons condemn'd by the Laws, is too well known; and how guilty and inſenſible the late King was of ſhedding of innocent blood, three Kingdoms have lamentable cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of Wards, Ideots and Mad men.</head>
               <p>AS to the Kings Prerogative in taking of Wards and their Marrages, it hath been granted him by Statute Law, as hereafter ſhall appear; and as to Ideots <hi>incompos mentis,</hi> and madmen, or ſuch as have by accident fallen into deſtraction, for the king to aſſume to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their eſtates, doubtleſs there is no Law for it (as I can remember) extant, otherwiſe to diſpoſe of their eſtates, but an accompt to be given to the next Heir at Law; and this of late years was reſolved by Mr. <hi>Calthrop</hi> his own Aturney in the Court of Wards, in the caſe of the Widdow of whoſe husband being burnt with powder at a muſter in <hi>Moorfields</hi> dyed, &amp; his wife for grief falling
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119898:78"/> diſtracted, the King gave her eſtate to one of his
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ramſey.</hi>
                  </note> ſervants a <hi>Scotch</hi>-man; but ſhe having many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and good friends, they petitioned the King therein, and in the end he was pleaſed to retract his grant as to the whole of the eſtate, but with this proviſo, that <hi>Ramſey</hi> ſhould have the uſe thereof du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Widows life, in caſe ſhe continued <hi>incompos,</hi> giving ſecurity for the repayment to the children; but the Gentlewomans friends found it unſafe to truſt ſo great an eſtate as 30000. <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>Ramſeys</hi> hands, and therefore with great difficulty they drew <hi>Ramſey</hi> to accept of 3000. <hi>l.</hi> ready money to to be quit of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the Kings aſſertion, that he was not accomptable for his actions to any but to God alone.</head>
               <p>AS to that odious poſition or rather Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical aſſertion, both of the Fathers and the Sons, that they were not accomptable
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119898:78"/> for their actions to any but to God alone, doubtleſs 'tis an impious poſition, and in the next degree to blaſphemy, and cannot be (without repentance) forgiven of God, nor forgotten of men, and thoſe of their ſubjects which felt the effects thereof. Should we longer inſiſt on this Theam, and produce proofs that Kings for their irregularities and Tyrannies, have in divers Kingdoms been call'd to account, they would amount to a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn. The Juſtice of <hi>Arragon,</hi> the Ephori amongſt the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> will ſoon evince and put this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion out of doubt; for Kings as well as ſubjects, both by Gods Laws and mans, are under the Law; and in this kingdom and many other well regulated Soveraignties, they have been often over-ruled, withſtood in their exorbitancies, ſued at Law and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and ſome depoſed, expeld and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to death; and ſhould it not be ſo, Subjects would be no other then inanimate ſlaves; ſure we are, Almighty God never impowered Kings with ſuch abſolute So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty that might enable them to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on their ſubjects without controule. <hi>Saul</hi> made a raſh vow (as a Law to the <hi>Iſaelites)</hi> that none ſhould eat any food
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119898:79"/> all the day until the evening but he ſhould die; <hi>Ionathan,</hi> being then abſent &amp; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, had dipt his rod in a Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb and taſted it; but being told of his Fathers Law, he anſwered the people, My Father troubles <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and indeed ſuch troublers there are amongſt kings; howſoever <hi>Ionathan</hi> was ſentenced to death; but the people withſtood the king, and ſwore that a hair of his head ſhould not fall, and they reſcued him in the face of the king; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſhould not there be ſome one other power in a kingdom to curbe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule the exorbitancies of irregular kings (for few of them are Saints) no man ſhould be exempted from their oppreſſions; and therefore <hi>Bracton</hi> delivers it as the law of the Land, that in ſuch caſes the Barons or Parliament ought not onely to withſtand oppreſſive kings, but to call them to account for their miſdemeanors, which may ſuffice to ſhow how much the two late kings were miſtaken in this their Tyrannous aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Now Gentleman Royaliſts, theſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Rights (as you would have them) ſo often treated on, utterly diſſonant to the Laws of the Land, whereunto particularly I have briefly made anſwer, are thoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119898:79"/> Prerogatives wherewith you would have inveſted the late king as his indubitable birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights, and inſeparables of his Crown, for which you ſtill conſtantly aver he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peld to fight, and your ſelves with him to uphold them; where I muſt by the way remember you of a time, when he ſhamed not to <note n="*" place="margin">Vide, <hi>The Kings Coyn at</hi> Oxford.</note> divulge it to the whole Nation, that he fought for the Proteſtant Religion, the Laws of the Land, and Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament (for he was not to ſeek wherein to pleaſe the people, and win them to his cauſe, though never ſo unjuſt) when as in truth he fought againſt all thoſe three, and ſo long as untill he could fight no more; but by what law or reaſon other then his own, none may better know then your ſelves, which as well as infinite others that oppoſed him, have felt the fruits of your unadviſedneſs, &amp; the effects of his obduracy, his cunning and crafty fetches to attract friends for backing of an unlimited Soveraignty, to which had he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, it would have been no other then too heavie a burthen for him to bear, a ſting in his own conſcience, &amp; a ſore in yours, which you will all finde, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to open the eyes of your underſtanding, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119898:80"/> enable you to ſee how you have bin decoyed in with Oathes, Proteſtations, and hopes of preferment, &amp; made the inſtruments of your own Invaſſalage. This if you believe not to have been the deſign, yet you may finde it legible, not onely in the claims and pretences he made to thoſe illegal and irrational Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives before recited, but more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently figured in that bloody Rubrick of a continued War, which he ſo long waged to be abſolute maſter of them, and conſequenly over all the free people of <hi>England.</hi> Thus have I ſhewed you how invalid the grounds are whereon you continue to inſiſt in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying the late king and your ſelves; how diſſonant, and contrary to the Laws, uſuages, and Statutes of the land; ſuch was the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and providence of our ancient Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in all their enactings, evermore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the common intereſt before the kings, though they failed not to gratifie them (as they found them compliable, to the redreſs of the publick grievances) with many Royal immunities, as we may finde them regiſtred in the Statutes at large, on the Title of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, ſome whereof I think fit here to preſent to your view, that ſo you may judge whether Sir <hi>Walter Rawly</hi> was not in the right, who avoucheth that few of our kings
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119898:80"/> but have gotten ground and improved their Soverainties meerely by their Parliaments, &amp; as I verily believe none more then the late unfortunate King, had he been pleaſed, (in imitation of Queen <hi>Elizabeth)</hi> to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with the late Parliament. But as to his Prerogative of Wardſhips and Marriages, they were firſt conferr'd on our Kings 17 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, their <hi>primer ſeſsion,</hi> 52. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, the tuition of Ideots and diſtracted perſons, 17. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 32. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, but with ſeveral proviſo's of accompts to be made to the next Heirs of Ideots, and the children of him that was <hi>incompos mentis.</hi> As to wracks of Sea, Whales &amp;c. they were given by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament to <hi>Edward</hi> the Second the 17 of his Raign; Felons goods the 9 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. power to make Juſtices of peace; 27. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the Legitimation of the Kings children born be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas; 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Tonage and Pondage to <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>pro tempore,</hi> yet granted to every of his Succeſſors by the meer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of their Parliaments, though the late King challenged it as his own right. I may not omit farther to inform you, that this Nation hath not been ſo much abuſed and deceived by any one proficient in our Laws, as by that falſe and jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Judge <hi>Ienkins,</hi> who in his <hi>Lex</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lex Terrae, <hi>a moſt vile and fraudulent peice.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Terrae,</hi> by his
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119898:81"/> accumulation of ſeveral Statutes, inſinuates and endeavors to make the Kings power abſolute, and conſequently the people mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Slaves and Vaſſals, alledging this and that to be the Law of the Land, which is not or ever was, taking his Authorities and Authors by piece-meals, curtaling the Statutes in their ſenſe, without the explanation of their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and intents; whereby (on my own knowledge) he hath deceived and prevailed on the belief of many in the Nation: But not longer to inſiſt on this ſubject, I ſhall onely ſay, that the Soverainty of our kings hath been ever of a mixt nature and not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute; and as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirms of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies in his Chapter <hi>De Romano Pontifiee, Monarchiam temperatam &amp; mixtam inter Ariſtocratiam &amp; Democratiam, ſemper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem eſſe puts:</hi> That a Monarchie mixt and tempered between an <hi>Ariſtocratical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and a <hi>Democratical,</hi> is the beſt of all Governments: ſo am I bold to avouch ſuch hath ever been the nature of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soverainty; would the late King have ſo conceived of its conſtitution, or given credit to the old learned Lawyers, <hi>viz. Bracton, Fleta, Fortiſcue,</hi> and many others; for the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have originally received their power from the people; <hi>Poteſtatem à populo effluxam Rex habet, quo non licet
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119898:81"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>poteſtate alia populo ſuo dominari, Fort. de leg. Aug.</hi> The King hath his power from the people, and ought not to govern them but by that Power and Law which he had from them; though Royaliſts generally have otherwiſe conceived thereof, ſuppoſing that the King cannot be a King, unleſs he be abſolute in power and command over the people: which was the error or rather wilfulneſs of the late King, who knew not or would not know the extent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soveraignty; but what out of his own inclinations, and others infuſions he was induced to believe, that he could not rule otherwiſe then by a plenary power: which is moſt dangerous to himſelf: for <hi>plenitudo poteſtatis, eſt plenitudo tempeſtatis,</hi> and enables him to deſtroy himſelf at his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, though the late King conceived otherwiſe, and that to be ſubject to the controule of a Court of Parliament, he could be no more then a mock-King, or a Duke of <hi>Venice;</hi> And certainly the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the people thought no leſs; and that a king was ſuch a ſupernatural and Divine creature (not made up of ſinful fleſh and blood like other men) as the poor woman conceived of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, who riding in progreſs through a Country
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119898:82"/> Village, attended with a great train of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, the Woman cryed out, Shew me the king; which of theſe is the king? He (quoth a foot-man) whom thou ſeeſt with a Feather in his Cap and a blew Ribban about his neck; Whoo! crys out the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, will you make me believe the Moon is made of Cheeſe; that's a very man, or elſe I never ſaw one in all my life; And the ſilly ſoul was in the right; for kings in their humane nature, are no other then mortal men, though in their other capacity (as they are kings the beſt of men in Supremacy) yet the worſt, if they neglect the duty of that great Office wherewith they are inveſted (by Gods appointment) for the publick good, more then their own; but I have taken too much liberty in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiating my ſelf on a ſubject ſo often treated of; though my deſign therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not beyond my affection, which hath lead me rather to perſwade by the ſoft Argument of Law and Reaſon, then in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of language to exclaim againſt any miſtaken in their opinions; not doubting that either themſelves or any other (on due conſideration) will tax me for imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency; when as 'tis well known the whole ſtate of the old Controverſie (ſince the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119898:82"/> of the late Parliament) hath been and is aſſidually revived by Royaliſts, and a new diſconted ſort of male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which forbear not to juſtifie the late King in all his errors, and condemn the Parliament for invading his juſt and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prerogatives; ſo that what and how many ſoever they are, they muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect but that of neceſſity there will new An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers be made (though upon the old matter) to new objections, which may ſatisfie all ſuch as out of the over-fineneſs and ſharpneſs of their wits, will cenſure whatſoever hath been afore ſaid on a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject long ſince determined, to be both needleſs and impertinent; But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude;</p>
               <p>It now onely remains, that we proceed to the Law of God and by Scriptural proof to facillitate a reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Royaliſts and that party which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to the preſent Government, wherein I ſhall briefly ſhew firſt the juſtneſs and lawfulneſs of their cordial ſubmiſſion to the powers in being; ſecondly, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their union one with the other, with the profit which thereby will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the mutual benefit of the whole Nation, not doubting but that by this little
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119898:83"/> which hath been ſpoken as concerning the Royal Prerogatives, they may receive ſome kind of ſatisfaction, that neither the Kings Intereſts in them were ſufficient grounds whereon to lay the foundation of thoſe bloody wars he ſo long waged againſt the great Judicature of the Nation, or that they were ſo valid in Law as to warrant Royaliſts to aſſiſt him to win them by the ſword: That controverſie being long ſince decided, and the Power of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in other hands; yet in a little let us now examine to whom in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience we all ought to yield our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> 13. on this very ſubject of obedience to Authority, preſcribes this as a general rule to all men, viz. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers;</hi> The reaſon of this Precept fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, viz. <hi>for there is no power but of God;</hi> And thereupon he infers, <hi>Therefore ye muſt needs be ſubject not onely for wrath but for conſcience ſake;</hi> and to this he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts <hi>Timothy</hi> to pray for a bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all thoſe in Authority: Now if Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts make queſtion, (as uſually they do) of the lawfulneſs of the preſent Authority, and ſay
'tis uſurpatious and unlawful, then they fall foul on Gods Oordinance, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119898:83"/> they queſtion S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the very reaſon of obedience in the Text, <hi>viz. for the powers that are, are the Ordinance of God:</hi> Now that this may more evidently appear, upon what a rock Royaliſts fall, by calling into queſtion the lawfulneſs of the preſent powers, I ſhall intreat them to take it into their ſecond conſiderations, whether then the Apoſtle was not out of the way, when he delivered this Doctrine of Obedience to Authority to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men the Jews, which was in the raigns of <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> both which came to their powers meerly by uſurpation and the ſword; but theſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours being in poſſeſſion, S. <hi>Paul</hi> takes no exception (as Royaliſts do) againſt their unlawful coming into power, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns obedience to be yielded to them; and can any of them poſitively and of truth affirm, that the powers of this Common-wealth are not devolved and confer'd on the States here by the Ordinance of God? <hi>Bucer</hi> on this very Text. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. ſays, That when the queſtion is, whom we ſhould obey, we ought not to queſtion, what he is that exerciſeth the power, or in what manner he diſpenſeth it; but it only ſufficeth thoſe which live under it that he hath power;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119898:84"/> for if any man hath obtained power, its then out of doubt, that he received that power of God; and then without farther ſcruple, thou muſt yield thy obedience to him and heartily obey him: And 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that when Chriſt and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preach't the Goſpel, it was at that very time that the <hi>Romans</hi> by plain Conqueſt and Uſurpation had gotten the poſſeſſion of all the Territory of <hi>Iudea;</hi> neither of them did then teach or diſſwade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their obedience to them, or that they ſhould not yield ſubmiſſion to thoſe that had Tyrannically obtained their power by the ſword; for 'tis plain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. that Chriſt did teach that Tribute was due unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and he himſelf paid it: Again, <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Be ye ſubject either to the King as Suprem, or unto Governors as thoſe which are ſent of him.</hi> It would be ſuperfluous longer to inſiſt on this ſubject, on which ſo much hath been expoſed to the publick view; it may therefore ſuffice without other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then ſuch as our bleſſed Saviour and his Apoſtels taught and practiſed, to perſwade obedience to powers in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing: Onely I ſhall cloſe up this hearty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſs to all Royaliſts with a piece of a Speech delivered by a Learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119898:84"/> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mr <hi>Thomas Warmiſtry</hi> in the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1640.</note>; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>The Law of God in Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is the main and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral root and trunk; and all good Laws are banches that grow from thence; and whatſoever hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Conſtitutions cannot either in a direct line or collateral derive themſelvs from them, are baſtard Iſſues and ſhameful to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the Law-makers ſins in framing of them; yet the difficulty of Government is to be conſidered, and many things to be born with; for though they have no ground in Gods Law for the injunction, but are meerly frivolous, and perhaps bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome; yet if their Authority diſables them to make it, and enjoyns me to no Act contrary to my allegeance to God, it is their ſin, but my affliction, and muſt be born as other calamities; for though that law hath no good end, yet my obedience hath; Obedience it ſelf is a good and laudable thing, and I may have the end of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing order or preſerving peace, and avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturbance in the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, of preventing ſcandal and the like, which are ends preſcribed by Gods Law to regulate and frame our actions by: All things are not to be turned upſide down
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119898:85"/> upon every inconvenience that may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in a Law, whether it be Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or civil; for beſides that there are few that are fit Judges of a Law: that may be unlawful for Governours to command, which yet is not unlawful but expedient for me to obey being commanded; as it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for <hi>Pharoah</hi> to command the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to make Brick without Straw (as being tyrannons) and ſo ſinful in him, as it was unlawful: but rather commendable in them to obey it as far as they could; and S. <hi>Paul</hi> will have ſervants to be obedient unto their Maſters, though they be froward and perverſe. Indeed, if they enjoyn me to do any thing wherein I ſhould offend againſt Gods Laws in the leaſt degree; no pretence of any, though never ſo many or ſo great good ends, muſt make me withdraw my allegeance from him, and pay it to humane powers; The authority of all men is limited, and ſo muſt our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them be alſo. The Supream power of God is the foundation of all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and therefore our duty unto that muſt be preferr'd in the firſt place, and without all leave or exception whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: peace muſt be maintain'd with the rules of piety and truſt; and any ſcandal
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:119898:85"/> to my brother, muſt rather be admitted then I ſhould prevent it without Gods leave: The rule of Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> is good here, <hi>Sicut libertas charitati, ita charitas fidei ſubjicienda eſt;</hi> yet in this caſe I am to diſobey, as modeſtly and as inoffenſively, and with as much ſhew of reverence to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate as may ſtand with our duty unto God; yet reſolutely too, not faintly or fearfully, as the three children unto <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 3. 17, &amp;c. And where we cannot yield obedience, we muſt yield the third duty of ſubjection; eſpecially where the Authority is abſolute and ſupream under God, which may be variouſly ſtated according to the Laws and Cuſtoms of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Countries and Dominions; then in caſe we cannot obey, we ought not to reſiſt but ſuffer, and yield a paſſive obedience where we may not yield an active one, according to the rule of Gods Word, <hi>They that reſiſt, ſhall receive unto themſelves damnation.</hi>
                  </q> Thus Royaliſts and all may ſee the judgement of a Gentleman of temper and learning, concerning obedience to be given to powers and Magiſtrates in being.</p>
               <p>I come now to the neceſſity of Royaliſts obedience to the preſent Government, with the profit and ſecurity that of courſe will
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119898:86"/> acrew to themſelves and the whole Nation, by their cordial conjuncture and compliance with the preſent powers; As to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity thereof I ſhall ſay no more, but that if they continue obſtinate and fix'd to their erroneous principles, and look back with <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, to him that claims as heir to the late unfortunate king, the conſequences and ſad effects whereof are particularly layd down in the former diſcourſe, if they be not hardned and paſt underſtanding, they will make the beſt of them to tremble to think upon the iſſues, whenſoever he comes in by their aſſiſtance (though ſurely very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) and their poſterity will doubtleſs curſe the time that ever they had ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as were the unhappy Authors of their invaſſaladge, and the betrayers of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon freedoms of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; which of neceſſity muſt follow whenſover the <hi>Scotch</hi> Pretender comes in by the ſword; ſo that the neceſſity of their compliance depends on this hinge onely, their preſent conjuncture with the preſent eſtabliſhment, ſince this ſtate cannot be ſecure ſo long as ſuch a numerous party of rotten hearts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, lurking in all corners of the Land, and lying at catch (on all opportunities) to diſturb the preſent ſettlement; for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119898:86"/> whereof, it hath been the advice of none of the worſt heads, on their next di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance or inſurrection, to proſcribe not onely all ſuch as ſhall be ſuſpected, but to take the courſe of Juſtice with thoſe that ſhall be known actors in any ſuch attempt; neither let any of them think this courſe ſtrange, ſince there is no reaſon to be given to cheriſh the Viper too long in the boſom of the Nation, leaſt in the end he eats through the bowels thereof; and as a wiſe man ſays, <hi>What wiſdom or providence can it be for this State to ſuffer ſuch to live amongſt them that will not co-operate, act, and joyn with the preſent powers?</hi> And what ſenſe is there, that after ſo bloody and rapacious a war ended, and peace reſettled, that if Royaliſts will, they may live quietly and peaceably, yet cannot forebear to ſpit their venome againſt thoſe which have reſcued them from invaſſalage; why then ſhould others be ſeen in unlawful things for their benefit, which refuſe to do right to others and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</p>
               <p>Gentlemen Royaliſts, I have now done, and more I would be willing to do for you, may it be to your advantage; but I know not a more ready way thereunto then at
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119898:87"/> leaſt to adviſe you to ſit quiet, or cordially to employ your ſelves in the publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I wiſh you all to call to minde, the late baniſhment of the <hi>Moors,</hi> out of the Kingdom of <hi>Granado</hi> into <hi>Africa,</hi> for no other cauſe but that the
<note n="*" place="margin">Philip the Second.</note> King could not convert them from their <hi>Mahometan</hi> to the Roman Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; a puniſhment that at beſt will befall you, whenſoever you ſhall be found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of any new diſturbance. On this conſideration I leave it to your ſelves to make judgement whether there be not a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of your timely compliance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture with the reſt of the Nation, that ſtands firm and faithful to the preſent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; under which we are all bound to give God the glory and praiſe, that ſince the ſheathing of that raging and bloody ſword of the late kings, we may if we liſt live quietly, enjoy the benefit of our old Laws (if not better) and the peace of our own houſes in ſecurity; bleſſings which of late years we had not, neither can we ever have them by the way you perſerve to walk in, and wiſh for by re-introducing Regal Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny inſeparably united to the Scepters of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119898:87"/> moſt Kings, but undoubtedly to all thoſe which are brought in by the power of the ſword: from ſuch, that our good God will deliver us, ſhall be the hearty prayers of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, moſt devoted to ſerve you in all honeſt and juſt Endeavors. T. L. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
